<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          version="5.0" revision="5.1" arch="assembly">

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><?tdg-refentrytitle?></refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo role="element">transform</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo role="pattern">db.transform</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo role="class">assembly</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname><?tdg-refname?></refname>
  <refpurpose><?tdg-refpurpose?></refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<?tdg-refsynopsisdiv?>

<refsection condition="ref.description">
<title>Description</title>


<para>A <tag>transform</tag> can be applied in two different ways, one
to convert non-DocBook content to DocBook, and the other to transform
DocBook content into a different instance of DocBook.</para>

<para>If the <tag class="attribute">grammar</tag> attribute is
specified, then the <tag>transform</tag> specified by the
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute is applied to any
<tag>resource</tag> elements with a matching
<tag class="attribute">grammar</tag> attribute to convert them to
DocBook for inclusion. This could be used to convert DITA files to
DocBook, for example.</para>

<para>If the <tag class="attribute">name</tag> attribute is specified
instead, then the <tag>transform</tag> is applied to any
<tag>module</tag> whose <tag>output</tag> element includes a <tag
class="attribute">transform</tag> attribute whose value matches the name.
This allows the content of a resource to be filtered or rearranged
before being output to the assembled DocBook document.</para>

Change the grammar attribute description to something like: "resource elements with a matching grammar attribute value will have this
transform applied to them during assembly to convert them to DocBook".

Change the name attribute description to something like: "output elements with a matching transform attribute value will have this
transform applied to the content of its parent module element when outputting the assembly."

<para>A <tag>transform</tag> specifies a mechanism for converting one format into
another during the assembly process. For example, if a <tag>module</tag> identifies
a resource in a foreign grammar, then a <tag>transform</tag> can be used to identify
the transformation that will convert the foreign grammar into DocBook.</para>

<refsection>
<title>Processing expectations</title>

<para>Never rendered.</para>

</refsection>

<?tdg-attributes?>
<?tdg-parents?>
<?tdg-children?>

</refsection>

<?tdg-seealso?>

<refsection condition="ref.examples">
<title>Examples</title>

<para>This example would apply the <uri>dita2docbook.xsl</uri>
transform to any resources that have a <tag
class="attribute">grammar</tag> attribute of
“<literal>dita</literal>”.</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<transform grammar="dita" href="dita2docbook.xsl"/>]]></programlisting>

<para>This example would apply the <uri>flatten-sections.xsl</uri>
transform to the content of any <tag>module</tag> that has an
<tag>output</tag> child element that includes a <tag
class="attribute">transform</tag> attribute with the value
“<literal>flatten</literal>”.</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<transform name="flatten" href="flatten-sections.xsl"/>]]></programlisting>
</refsection>
</refentry>
