<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
          xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
          xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
<info>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><?tdg-refentrytitle?></refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo role='element'>subject</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo role='pattern'>db.subject</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname><?tdg-refname?></refname>
  <refpurpose><?tdg-refpurpose?></refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<?tdg-refsynopsisdiv?>

<refsection condition='ref.description'>
<title>Description</title>


<para>A <quote>subject</quote> categorizes or describes the topic of a
document, or section of a document. In DocBook, a <tag>Subject</tag>
is defined by the <tag>SubjectTerm</tag>s that it contains.
</para>
<para>Subject terms should be drawn from a controlled vocabulary, such
as the <emphasis>Library of Congress Subject Headings</emphasis>. If an outside
vocabulary is not appropriate, a local or institutional subject set
should be created.
</para>
<para>The advantage of a controlled vocabulary is that it places the document
into a known subject space. Searching the subject space with a particular
subject term will find <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the documents that claim
to have that subject. There's no need to worry about terms that are
synonymous with the search item, or homophones of the search term.
</para>
<para>All of the <tag>SubjectTerm</tag>s in a <tag>Subject</tag> should
describe the same subject, and be from the <emphasis>same controlled
vocabulary</emphasis>.
</para>

<refsection><title>Processing expectations</title>
<para><?tdg gentext='format.context'?>
Subjects are rarely displayed to a reader. Usually, they
are reserved for searching and retrieval purposes.
</para>
<para>Unlike <tag>Keyword</tag>s, which may be chosen freely, 
subject terms should come from a controlled vocabulary.
</para>
<para>In order to assure that typographic or other errors are not introduced
into the subject terms, they should be compared against the controlled
vocabulary by an external process.
</para>
</refsection>


<?tdg-attributes?>
<?tdg-parents?>
<?tdg-children?>

</refsection>

<?tdg-seealso?>

<!-- FIXME: add examples -->

</refentry>
