<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
          xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
          xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
<info>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><?tdg-refentrytitle?></refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo role='element'>entry</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo role='pattern'>db.entry</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname><?tdg-refname?></refname>
  <refpurpose><?tdg-refpurpose?></refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<?tdg-refsynopsisdiv?>

<refsection condition='ref.description'>
<title>Description</title>


<!-- Fragment document type declaration subset:
ArborText, Inc., 1988-1998, v.4002
<!DOCTYPE SET PUBLIC "-//Davenport//DTD DocBook V3.0//EN" [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "/Documents/books/dbnutshell/entities/entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
-->
<?Pub CX set(book(bookinfo()part()part(title()reference(title()refentry(refmeta()refnamediv()refsynopsisdiv()refsect1(title()?>
<para><tag>Entry</tag> is a cell in a table.</para>
<para>Each <tag>Entry</tag> may specify its starting column.  Entries
that do not explicitly specify a starting column begin implicitly in the column
that is immediately adjacent to the preceding cell. Note that 
<tag>Entry</tag>s with the 
<tag class="attribute">MoreRows</tag> attribute
from preceding rows implicitly occupy cells in the succeeding 
<tag>Row</tag>s.</para>
<para>A <tag>row</tag> is not required to be full.  It is legal for some entries to be
completely absent (at the beginning, middle, or end of a row).</para>
<sidebar xml:id="pernicious">
<title>Pernicious Mixed Content</title>
<para>The content model of the <tag>Entry</tag> element exhibits a
nasty peculiarity that we call “pernicious mixed content”.<footnote>
<para>A term coined by Terry Allen.</para>
</footnote></para>
<para>Every other element in DocBook contains either block elements or inline
elements (including text) unambiguously.  In these cases, the meaning
of line breaks and spaces are well understood; they are insignificant between
block elements and significant (to the <acronym>SGML</acronym> parser, anyway) where inline
markup can occur.</para>
<para>Table entries are different; they can contain either block or inline
elements, but not both at the same time.  In other words, one
<tag>entry</tag> in a table might contain a paragraph or a list while another contains
simply text or another inline markup, but no single <tag>Entry</tag>
can contain both.</para>
<para>Because the content model of an <tag>Entry</tag> allows both kinds
of markup, each time the <acronym>SGML</acronym> parser encounters an <tag>Entry</tag>,
it has to decide what variety of markup it contains.  <acronym>SGML</acronym> parsers are forbidden
to use more than a single token of lookahead to reach this decision. In practical
terms, what this means is that a line feed or space after an
<tag>entry</tag> start tag causes the parser to decide that the cell contains inline
markup.  Subsequent discovery of a paragraph or another block element causes
a parsing error.</para>
<para>All of these are legal: 
<screen>
<![CDATA[
<entry>3.1415927</entry>
<entry>General <emphasis>#PCDATA</emphasis></entry>
<entry><para>A paragraph of text
</para></entry>
]]>
</screen>
</para>
<para>However, each of these is an error:  <screen>&lt;entry>                <lineannotation>
Error, cannot have a line break before a block element</lineannotation>
<![CDATA[<para>A paragraph of text.
</para></entry>

<entry><para>A paragraph of text.]]>
&lt;/para>               <lineannotation>Error, cannot have a line break between block elements
</lineannotation>
<![CDATA[<para>A paragraph of text.
</para></entry>

]]><?ORA break="sidebar"?><![CDATA[<entry><para>A paragraph of text.]]>
&lt;/para>               <lineannotation>Error, cannot have a line break after a block element
</lineannotation>
<![CDATA[</entry>]]></screen></para>

<para>When designing a <acronym>DTD</acronym>, it is wise to avoid pernicious mixed
content.  Unfortunately, the only way to correct the pernicious
mixed content problem that already exists in DocBook is
to require some sort of wrapper (a block element, or an inline
like <tag>Phrase</tag>) around text within table
<tag>Entry</tag>s.  This is annoying and inconvenient in
a great many tables in which text cells predominate and, in
addition, differ from
<acronym>CALS</acronym>.</para>
</sidebar>

<refsection><title>Processing expectations</title>
<para><?tdg gentext='calssemantics'?>
</para>
<para>The content of <tag>Entry</tag> is formatted to fit within the table
cell that it occupies.  Horizontal and vertical spanning may allow the
content of an <tag>Entry</tag> to occupy several physical cells.
</para>
</refsection>

<?tdg-attributes?>
<?tdg-parents?>
<?tdg-children?>

</refsection>

<?tdg-seealso?>

<!-- FIXME: add examples -->

</refentry>
