<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:id="preface">
<?dbhtml filename="ch00.html"?>
<info>
<title>Preface</title>
<pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
<releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<para>DocBook provides a system for writing structured documents using
<acronym>XML</acronym>. It is particularly well-suited to books and
papers about computer hardware and software, though it is by no means
limited to them. Because it is a large and robust format,
and because its main structures correspond to
the general notion of what constitutes a book, DocBook has been
adopted by a large and constantly growing community of authors. DocBook is
supported <quote>out of the box</quote> by a wide range of tools, both open
source and commercial. In short, DocBook is an easy-to-understand and
widely used schema. Hundreds (perhaps thousands) of organizations use
DocBook for millions of pages of documentation, in various print and
online formats, worldwide.
</para>

<section xml:id="pref-whyread">
<title>Why Read This Book?</title>

<para>This book is designed to be the clear, concise, normative reference to
the DocBook schema. This book is the official documentation for DocBook.
</para>

<para>We hope to answer, definitively, all the questions you might
have about all the elements and attributes in DocBook. In particular,
we cover the following subjects:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The general nature of DocBook. With over 400 elements,
DocBook can be a bit overwhelming at first. We quickly get you up to
speed on how the pieces fit together.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>How to write DocBook documents. Where should you start
and what should you do?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Parsing and validation. After you've written a
document, how can you tell if it really conforms to the DocBook
schema?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>How to publish DocBook documents. After you've written
one, what do you do with it? We provide a guide to using some popular
free tools to publish DocBook documents both in print and on the
Web.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Customizing the schema. Many individuals and
corporations have standardized on the DocBook schema. Whether your
subject matter is computer software documentation or not,
we explain how you can write a <quote>customization layer</quote> to
tailor DocBook explicitly for your information.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Understanding all of the elements. Each element is
extensively documented, including the intended semantics and the
purpose of all its attributes. An example of proper usage is given
for every element. The parameter entities and character entities are
also described.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Stylesheets. The DocBook XSL Stylesheets, part of the
<link xlink:href="http://docbook.sf.net/">DocBook
project</link> at <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</link>,
have become a defacto standard way to process DocBook. We describe them
briefly.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Finally, we direct you to other places you
can go for all the latest info.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-bookaud">
<title>This Book's Audience</title>

<para>We expect that most readers will have some familiarity with
<acronym>XML</acronym>. Even if your experience goes no farther than
writing a few <acronym>HTML</acronym> pages, you're probably in good
shape. Although we provide an introduction to <acronym>XML</acronym>,
and structured markup, this book may not
suffice as your only tutorial about <acronym>XML</acronym>.
This depends, naturally, on your needs and
experience. For a list of some other good resources, consult <xref
linkend="app-resources"/>.
</para>

<note xml:id="sgml">
<para>The previous edition of this book described some of the SGML-specific
features available to users of the DocBook <acronym>DTD</acronym> versions 4.x
and earlier. In this edition, we don't cover SGML at all. Starting with DocBook
V5.0, DocBook is normatively an XML vocabulary.</para>
</note>

<para>Some sections of this book describe tools and applications. For
the most part, these are Microsoft Windows or <acronym>UNIX</acronym>
applications, although there's nothing about DocBook that makes it
unsuitable for the Mac or <acronym>VM/CMS</acronym> or any other
operating system of your choice.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-organization">
<title>Organization of This Book</title>

<para>This book is divided into three parts.
<citetitle>Part I: Introduction </citetitle> is an introduction to
structured markup and DocBook:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-gsxml"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>A quick introduction to structured markup.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-create"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>How to make DocBook documents.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-parse"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>Parsing and validating DocBook documents.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-publish"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>How to publish DocBook documents.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-customizing"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>How to customize DocBook.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para condition="refpages"><citetitle>Part II: Reference</citetitle>
<phrase condition="online">is a complete reference to every element
and parameter entity in the DocBook V5.0 schema.</phrase>
<phrase condition="print">is a complete reference to every element in
the DocBook V5.0 schema.</phrase>
</para>

<variablelist condition="refpages">
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ref-element"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>A reference guide to the DocBook elements.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para><citetitle>Part III: Appendixes</citetitle> discusses other resources:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-install"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>How to install DocBook and the stylesheets.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-versions"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>A guide to DocBook versions, including a summary of the features
expected in future releases.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-resources"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>Other resources.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-cdrom"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>The first edition of the book included a CD-ROM. This appendix still
exists, so that the labels of following appendixes remains the same. There
is no CD-ROM for this edition of the book.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-interchange"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>An interchange checklist. Things to consider when you're sharing
DocBook documents with others.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><xref linkend="quickref"/></term>
<listitem>
<para>A Quick Reference to the elements in DocBook.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>At the end of this book you'll find a <xref linkend="glossary"/> and an
<!-- YES, THIS IS DUPLICATED ONCE WITH THE LINK AND ONCE WITHOUT: -->
<phrase condition="online"><xref linkend="index"/>.</phrase>
<phrase condition="print">Index.</phrase>
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-conventions">
<title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A <tag role="nonexistant">monospaced font</tag> is used for element
and attribute names.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>A <literal>monospaced font</literal> is also used for program
examples, attribute value literals, start- and end-tags, and source
code example text.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>An <replaceable>italic monospaced font</replaceable> is used for
<quote>replaceable</quote> text or variables. Replaceable text is text
that describes something you're supposed to type, like a
<replaceable>filename</replaceable>, in which the word
<quote>filename</quote> is a placeholder for the actual
filename.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><filename>Italic</filename> is used for filenames and
(in the print version of the book) <acronym>URL</acronym>s.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem condition="print">
<para><link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/"><acronym>URL</acronym>s</link> are
presented in parentheses after the name of the resource they describe
in the print version of the book.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-getbook">
<title>Getting This Book</title>

<para>If you want to hold this book in your hand and flip through its
pages, you'll have to print it yourself. As of July, 2007, there are no
plans to publish it on dead trees again. Our immediate focus is on the
web presentation, but we do expect to provide a reasonable PDF version in
due course.</para>

<para>You can also get this book in electronic form, as a DocBook
document, and in <acronym>HTML</acronym> from this book's web site:
<uri xlink:href="http://docbook.org/">http://docbook.org/</uri>.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-getexamples">
<title>Getting Examples from This Book</title>

<para>All of the examples are online at the book's web site. You can
get the most up-to-date information about this book from the web site:
<link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/">http://docbook.org/</link>.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-getdocbook">
<title>Getting DocBook</title>

<para>You can get DocBook from 
<link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/">http://docbook.org/</link>.
It is also available from the official OASIS web site,
<link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/">http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/</link>.
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="pref-req-comments">
<title>Request for Comments</title>

<para>Please help us improve future editions of this book by reporting
any errors, inaccuracies, bugs, misleading or confusing statements,
and plain old typos that you find. An online errata list is maintained
at <link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/tdg5/errata.html"/>. Email
your bug reports and comments to us at
<email>bookcomments@docbook.org</email>.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="acknowledgements">
<title>Acknowledgements from the First Edition</title>

<section xml:id="pref-acknorm">
<title>Acknowledgements from Norm</title>

<para>This book has been in the works for a long time. It could not
have been completed without the help and encouragement of a lot of
people, most especially my wife, Deborah, who supported me through the
long hours and the late nights.
</para>
<para>
I also want to thank Lenny for collaborating with me and developing
real prose out of my rough outlines, cryptic email messages, and
scribbled notes.</para>
<para>
A number of people contributed technical feedback as this book
was being written, in particular Terry Allen and Eve Maler. I
owe most of what I know about <acronym>SGML</acronym> to them, and to the other
members of the Davenport Group who answered all my questions so
many years ago, especially Jon Bosak, Eduardo Guttentag, and
Murray Maloney. Paul Prescod, Mark Galassi, and Dave Pawson also
provided invaluable feedback on the technical review draft. It's
a better book because of them.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="pref-acklen">
<title>Acknowledgements from Lenny</title>

<para>My gratitude goes back to Dale Dougherty and Terry Allen, who
long ago encouraged me and the production department at O'Reilly to learn
<acronym>SGML</acronym>; and to Lar Kaufman, who also made large contributions to my 
knowledge and appreciation of <acronym>SGML</acronym>. But my greatest debt of thanks goes to 
Norm for all that he patiently taught me about DocBook, and for his
supreme graciousness in keeping me a part of this project. 
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="pref-ackboth">
<title>Acknowledgements from Norm and Lenny</title>

<para>
Thanks finally to the great people at O'Reilly who encouraged us to
write it (Frank Willison and Sheryl Avruch), agreed to edit it
(Frank), helped design it (Alicia Cech, who worked on the interior
design, and Edie Freeman, who designed the cover), proofed and
produced it (Chris Maden, Madeline Newell, and David Futato), and
indexed it (Ellen Troutman).
</para>
</section>
</section>

</preface>
