<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:id="preface">
<?dbhtml filename="ch00.html"?>
<info>
  <title>Preface</title>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<para>DocBook provides a system for writing structured documents using
<acronym>XML</acronym>. It is particularly well-suited to books and
papers about computer hardware and software, though it is by no means
limited to them. Because it is a large and robust format,
and because its main structures correspond to
the general notion of what constitutes a book, DocBook has been
adopted by a large and constantly growing community of authors. DocBook is
supported <quote>out of the box</quote> by a wide range of tools, both open
source and commercial. In short, DocBook is an easy-to-understand and
widely used schema. Hundreds (perhaps thousands) of organizations use
DocBook for millions of pages of documentation, in various print and
online formats, worldwide.
</para>

<section xml:id="pref-whyread">
  <title>Why Read This Book?</title>

  <para>This book is designed to be the clear, concise, normative reference to
  the DocBook schema. This book is the official documentation for DocBook.
  </para>

  <para>We hope to answer, definitively, all the questions you might
  have about all the elements and attributes in DocBook. In particular,
  we cover the following subjects:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>The general nature of DocBook. With over 400 elements,
    DocBook can be a bit overwhelming at first. We quickly get you up to
    speed on how the pieces fit together.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>How to write DocBook documents. Where should you start
    and what should you do?</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Parsing and validation. After you've written a
    document, how can you tell if it really conforms to the DocBook
    schema?</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>How to publish DocBook documents. After you've written
    one, what do you do with it? We provide a guide to using some popular
    free tools to publish DocBook documents both in print and on the
    Web.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Customizing the schema. Many individuals and
    corporations have standardized on the DocBook schema. Whether your
    subject matter is computer software documentation or not,
    we explain how you can write a <quote>customization layer</quote> to
    tailor DocBook explicitly for your information.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Understanding all of the elements. Each element is
    extensively documented, including the intended semantics and the
    purpose of all its attributes. An example of proper usage is given
    for every element.
  </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Stylesheets. The DocBook XSL Stylesheets, part of the
    <link xlink:href="http://docbook.sf.net/">DocBook
    project</link> at <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</link>,
    have become a defacto standard way to process DocBook. We describe them
    briefly.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Finally, we direct you to other places you
    can go for all the latest info.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-bookaud">
  <title>This Book's Audience</title>

  <para>We expect that most readers will have some familiarity with
  <acronym>XML</acronym>. Even if your experience goes no farther than
  writing a few <acronym>HTML</acronym> pages, you're probably in good
  shape. Although we provide an introduction to <acronym>XML</acronym>,
  and structured markup, this book may not
  suffice as your only tutorial about <acronym>XML</acronym>.
  This depends, naturally, on your needs and
  experience. For a list of some other good resources, consult <xref
  linkend="app-resources"/>.
  </para>

  <note xml:id="sgml">
    <para>The previous edition of this book described some of the SGML-specific
    features available to users of the DocBook <acronym>DTD</acronym> versions 4.x
    and earlier. In this edition, we don't cover SGML at all. Starting with DocBook
    V5.0, DocBook is normatively an XML vocabulary.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Some sections of this book describe tools and applications. For
  the most part, these are Microsoft Windows or <acronym>Linux</acronym>
  applications, although there's nothing about DocBook that makes it
  unsuitable for the Mac or any other
  operating system of your choice.
  </para>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-organization">
  <title>Organization of This Book</title>

  <para>This book is divided into three parts.
  <citetitle>Part I: Introduction </citetitle> is an introduction to
  structured markup and DocBook, and includes the following chapters:</para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="preface"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>This Preface.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-gsxml"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Getting Started with DocBook. This chapter combines and updates
      the information in the <quote>Getting Started with SGML/XML,</quote>
      <quote>Creating DocBook Documents,</quote>
      <quote>Parsing DocBook Documents,</quote> and
      <quote>Publishing DocBook Documents</quote> chapters from the First Edition,
      along with some of the information originally in Appendix A,
      <quote>Installation</quote>.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-customizing"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>How to Customize DocBook.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para condition="refpages"><citetitle>Part II: Reference</citetitle>
  <phrase condition="online">is a complete reference to every element
  and parameter entity in the DocBook V5.0 schema.</phrase>
  <phrase condition="print">is a complete reference to every element in
  the DocBook V5.0 schema.</phrase>
  </para>

  <variablelist condition="refpages">
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ref-element"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>A reference guide to the DocBook elements.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para><citetitle>Part III: Appendixes</citetitle> discusses other resources:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-versions"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>A guide to DocBook versions, including a summary of the features
      expected in future releases.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-resources"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Other resources.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-cdrom"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>The first edition of the book included a CD-ROM. This appendix still
      exists, so that the labels of following appendixes remains the same. There
      is no CD-ROM for this edition of the book.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-interchange"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>An interchange checklist. Things to consider when you're sharing
      DocBook documents with others.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="quickref"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>A Quick Reference to the elements in DocBook.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>At the end of this book you'll find a <xref linkend="glossary"/> and an
  <!-- YES, THIS IS DUPLICATED ONCE WITH THE LINK AND ONCE WITHOUT: -->
  <phrase condition="online"><xref linkend="index"/>.</phrase>
  <phrase condition="print">Index.</phrase>
  </para>
</section>

  <section>
    <title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

    <para>The following typographical conventions are used in this
    book:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Italic</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Indicates new terms, URLs, email addresses, filenames, and
          file extensions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>Constant width</literal></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for program listings, as well as within
          paragraphs to refer to element and attribute names, program
          examples, attribute value literals, start- and end-tags, and
          source code example text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><userinput>Constant width bold</userinput></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows commands or other text that should be typed literally by
          the user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><replaceable>Constant width italic</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows text that should be replaced with user-supplied
          values or by values determined by context. An example is
          <replaceable>filename</replaceable>, where the word
          <quote>filename</quote> is a placeholder for the actual
          filename.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <tip>
      <para>This icon signifies a tip, suggestion, or general note.</para>
    </tip>

    <caution>
      <para>This icon indicates a warning or caution.</para>
    </caution>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using Code Examples</title>

    <para>This book is here to help you get your job done. In general, you may
    use the code in this book in your programs and documentation. You do not
    need to contact us for permission unless you’re reproducing a significant
    portion of the code. For example, writing a program that uses several
    chunks of code from this book does not require permission. Selling or
    distributing a CD-ROM of examples from O’Reilly books does require
    permission. Answering a question by citing this book and quoting example
    code does not require permission. Incorporating a significant amount of
    example code from this book into your product’s documentation does require
    permission.</para>

    <para>We appreciate, but do not require, attribution. An attribution
    usually includes the title, author, publisher, and ISBN. For example:
    “<emphasis>DocBook: The Definitive Guide, Second Edition</emphasis> by Norman Walsh. Copyright 2009 O’Reilly Media, Inc., 978-0-596-8050-2-9.”</para>

    <para>If you feel your use of code examples falls outside fair use or the
    permission given above, feel free to contact us at
    <email>permissions@oreilly.com</email>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Safari® Books Online</title>

    <note role="safarienabled">
      <para>When you see a Safari® Books Online icon on the cover of your
      favorite technology book, that means the book is available online
      through the O’Reilly Network Safari Bookshelf.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Safari offers a solution that’s better than e-books. It’s a virtual
    library that lets you easily search thousands of top tech books, cut and
    paste code samples, download chapters, and find quick answers when you
    need the most accurate, current information. Try it for free at <link
    role="orm:hideurl:ital"
    xlink:href="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly">http://my.safaribooksonline.com</link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to Contact Us</title>

    <para>Please address comments and questions concerning this book to the
    publisher:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>O’Reilly Media, Inc.</member>

      <member>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</member>

      <member>Sebastopol, CA 95472</member>

      <member>800-998-9938 (in the United States or Canada)</member>

      <member>707-829-0515 (international or local)</member>

      <member>707 829-0104 (fax)</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>We have a web page for this book, where we list errata, examples,
    and any additional information. You can access this page at:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><link
      xlink:href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/&lt;catalog page&gt;"></link></member>
    </simplelist>

    <remark>Don’t forget to update the &lt;url&gt; attribute, too.</remark>

    <para>To comment or ask technical questions about this book, send email
    to:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><email>bookquestions@oreilly.com</email></member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>For more information about our books, conferences, Resource Centers,
    and the O’Reilly Network, see our web site at:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><link xlink:href="http://www.oreilly.com"></link></member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <para>
      <remark>TBD: Also, should Acknowledgments from first edition
      be included, too?</remark>
    </para>
  </section>
</preface>
