<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:id="preface">
<?dbhtml filename="ch00.html"?>
<info>
  <title>Preface</title>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<para>DocBook provides a system for writing structured documents using
<acronym>XML</acronym>. It is particularly well-suited to books and
papers about computer hardware and software, though it is by no means
limited to them. Because it is a large and robust format,
and because its main structures correspond to
the general notion of what constitutes a book, DocBook has been
adopted by a large and growing community of authors. DocBook is
supported <quote>out of the box</quote> by a wide range of tools, both open
source and commercial. In short, DocBook is an easy-to-understand and
widely used schema. Worldwide, hundreds (perhaps thousands) of organizations use
DocBook for millions of pages of documentation in a wide variety of print and
online formats.
</para>

<section xml:id="pref-whyread">
  <title>Why Read This Book?</title>

  <para>This book is designed to be the clear, concise, normative reference to
  the DocBook schema. This book is the official documentation for DocBook.
  </para>

  <para>We hope to answer, definitively, all the questions you might
  have about all the elements and attributes in DocBook. In particular,
  we cover the following subjects:</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term>Getting started with DocBook:</term>
    <listitem><para>With around 400 elements,
    DocBook can be a bit overwhelming at first. We get you up to
    speed quickly.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Writing DocBook documents:</term>
    <listitem><para>Where should you start
    and what should you do?</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Parsing and validating DocBook documents:</term>
    <listitem><para>After
    you've written a document, how can you tell if it really conforms
    to the DocBook schema?</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Publishing DocBook documents:</term>
    <listitem><para>After you've written
    one, what do you do with it? We introduce some popular
    free tools you can use to publish DocBook documents in print and various
    electronic formats.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Customizing the schema:</term>
    <listitem><para>Many individuals and
    corporations have created custom schemas based on DocBook.
    We show you how to write a <quote>customization layer</quote>
    to tailor DocBook for your content.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Understanding the elements:</term>
    <listitem><para>Each element is
    extensively documented, including the intended semantics and the
    purpose of all its attributes. An example of proper usage is included
    for most elements.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Using the DocBook stylesheets:</term>
    <listitem><para>The DocBook <acronym>XSL</acronym> Stylesheets,
    part of the <link xlink:href="http://docbook.sf.net/">DocBook
    project</link> at <link
    xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</link>, have
    become the de facto standard way to process DocBook. This book
    contains a brief description about using the stylesheets, but for
    detailed information we recommend Bob Stayton's excellent book,
    <citetitle>DocBook XSL: The Complete Guide</citetitle><biblioref
    linkend="Stayton07"/>.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Getting more information:</term>
    <listitem><para>Finally, we direct you to other places you
    can go for information about DocBook, <acronym>XML</acronym>, and
    other relevant topics.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>

<section xml:id="pref-bookaud">
  <title>This Book's Audience</title>

  <para>We expect that most readers will have some familiarity with
  <acronym>XML</acronym>. Even if your experience goes no farther than
  writing a few <acronym>HTML</acronym> pages, you're probably in good
  shape. If you're not already familiar with <acronym>XML</acronym>,
  there are many popular books, including Erik Ray's <citetitle
  >Learning XML</citetitle><biblioref linkend="Ray03"/>. For a list
  of other resources, consult <xref linkend="app-resources"/>.
  </para>

  <note xml:id="sgml">
    <para>The previous edition of this book described some of the SGML-specific
    features available to users of the DocBook <acronym>DTD</acronym> versions 4.x
    and earlier. In this edition, we don't cover <acronym>SGML</acronym> at all. Starting with DocBook
    <acronym>V5.0</acronym>, DocBook is normatively an <acronym>XML</acronym> vocabulary.</para>
  </note>

</section>

<section xml:id="pref-organization">
  <title>Organization of This Book</title>

  <para>This book is divided into three parts:</para>
  <para>
  <citetitle>Part I: Introduction </citetitle> is an introduction to
  DocBook and includes the following chapters:</para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-gsxml"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Getting Started with DocBook</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-create"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Creating DocBook Documents</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-parse"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Validating DocBook Documents</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ch-publish"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Publishing DocBook Documents</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-customizing"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Customizing DocBook</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para condition="refpages"><citetitle>Part II: Reference</citetitle>
  <phrase condition="online">is a complete reference to every element
  and parameter entity in the DocBook <acronym>V5.0</acronym> schema.</phrase>
  <phrase condition="print">is a complete reference to every element in
  the DocBook <acronym>V5.0</acronym> schema.</phrase>
  </para>

  <variablelist condition="refpages">
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="ref-element"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>A reference guide to the DocBook elements.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para><citetitle>Part III: Appendixes</citetitle>:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-install"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Describes how to install the DocBook schema and stylesheets.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-variants"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Describes DocBook variants and discusses future directions.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-resources"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Lists websites, books and other resources.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="app-interchange"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>An interchange checklist. Things to consider when sharing
      DocBook documents with others.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><xref linkend="gfdl"/></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>A copy of the GNU Free Documentation License.</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>At the end of this book you'll find a 
  <!-- YES, THESE ARE DUPLICATED ONCE WITH THE LINK AND ONCE WITHOUT: -->
  <phrase condition="online"><xref linkend="glossary"/></phrase>
  <phrase condition="print">Glossary</phrase>
  and an
  <phrase condition="online"><xref linkend="index"/>.</phrase>
  <phrase condition="print">Index.</phrase>
  </para>
</section>

  <section>
    <title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

    <para>The following typographical conventions are used in this
    book:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Italic</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Indicates new terms, <acronym>URL</acronym>s, email addresses, filenames, and
          file extensions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>Constant width</literal></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for program listings, as well as within
          paragraphs to refer to element and attribute names, program
          examples, attribute value literals, start- and end-tags, and
          source code example text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><userinput>Constant width bold</userinput></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows commands or other text that should be typed literally by
          the user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><replaceable>Constant width italic</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows text that should be replaced with user-supplied
          values or by values determined by context. An example is
          <replaceable>filename</replaceable>, where the word
          <quote>filename</quote> is a placeholder for the actual
          filename.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <tip>
      <para>This icon signifies a tip, suggestion, or general note.</para>
    </tip>

    <caution>
      <para>This icon indicates a warning or caution.</para>
    </caution>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using Code Examples</title>

    <para>This book is here to help you get your job done. In general, you may
    use the code in this book in your programs and documentation. You do not
    need to contact us for permission unless you’re reproducing a significant
    portion of the code. For example, writing a program that uses several
    chunks of code from this book does not require permission. Selling or
    distributing a CD-ROM of examples from O’Reilly books does require
    permission. Answering a question by citing this book and quoting example
    code does not require permission. Incorporating a significant amount of
    example code from this book into your product’s documentation does require
    permission.</para>

    <para>We appreciate, but do not require, attribution. An attribution
    usually includes the title, author, publisher, and ISBN. For example:
    <quote><citetitle>DocBook: The Definitive Guide, Second Edition</citetitle> by Norman Walsh. Copyright 2010 O’Reilly Media, Inc., ISBN: 978-0-596-8050-2-9.</quote></para>

    <para>If you feel your use of code examples falls outside fair use or the
    permission given above, feel free to contact us at
    <email>permissions@oreilly.com</email>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Safari® Books Online</title>

    <note role="safarienabled">
      <para>When you see a Safari® Books Online icon on the cover of your
      favorite technology book, that means the book is available online
      through the O’Reilly Network Safari Bookshelf.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Safari offers a solution that’s better than e-books. It’s a virtual
    library that lets you easily search thousands of top tech books, cut and
    paste code samples, download chapters, and find quick answers when you
    need the most accurate, current information. Try it for free at <link
    role="orm:hideurl:ital"
    xlink:href="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly">http://my.safaribooksonline.com</link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to Contact Us</title>

    <para>Please address comments and questions concerning this book to the
    publisher:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>O’Reilly Media, Inc.</member>

      <member>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</member>

      <member>Sebastopol, CA 95472</member>

      <member>800-998-9938 (in the United States or Canada)</member>

      <member>707-829-0515 (international or local)</member>

      <member>707 829-0104 (fax)</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>We have a web page for this book, where we list errata, examples,
    and any additional information. You can access this page at:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><link
      xlink:href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/&lt;catalog page&gt;"></link></member>
    </simplelist>

    <remark>Don’t forget to update the &lt;url&gt; attribute, too.</remark>

    <para>To comment or ask technical questions about this book, send email
    to:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><email>bookquestions@oreilly.com</email></member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>For more information about our books, conferences, Resource Centers,
    and the O’Reilly Network, see our web site at:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><link xlink:href="http://www.oreilly.com"></link></member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>

<para>This book wouldn't exist, there wouldn't have been any point in
writing it, were it not for DocBook's enthusiastic support from an
entire community of writers, engineers, managers, and other users. My
thanks to you all.</para>

<para>It also wouldn't exist if my wife was not so understanding and
supportive. Writing a book invariable takes more time and effort than
one imagines, time first borrowed from, then begged, and eventually
stolen from other activities. Thank you, Deb!</para>

<para>And, to conclude a series, it also wouldn't exist were it not
for Dick Hamilton's encouragement and hard work. Dick first persuaded me
to complete a second edition in print, then offered to publish it. He
negotiated with O'Reilly, agreed to edit it, and wrote more of it than
he could be persuaded to take credit for. Thank you, Dick.</para>

<para>Several sections in this book use material from <link
xlink:href="http://docbook.org/docs/howto/"><quote>DocBook V5.0: The
Transition Guide,</quote></link> also known as the <quote>DocBook
How-to.</quote> Thanks to Jirka Kosek and Michael
Smith for their work on the How-to.
</para>

<para>Thanks to Nancy Harrison, Scott Hudson, Mauritz Jeanson, Jirka
Kosek, and Larry Rowland for their technical review of the book.
</para>

<para>Thanks to Bob Stayton for being Secretary to the Technical
Committee and to Scott Hudson for chairing the eLearning and Publisher's
Subcommittees and for being the driving force behind those two initiatives.
Thanks also to the entire DocBook Technical Committee for
contributing time every month to the continued maintenance of DocBook.
</para>

</section>
</preface>
