<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY version "5.0">
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:id="ch-gsxml">
<?dbhtml filename="ch01.html"?>
<title>Getting Started with <acronym>DocBook</acronym></title>
<info>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<para><indexterm xml:id="XMLgetstart" class="startofrange">
<primary>DocBook</primary><secondary>getting started</secondary>
</indexterm>This chapter provides an overview of DocBook, including
information about how to create, parse, and publish DocBook documents.
It assumes you have a basic understanding of XML. If you're not already familiar with
<acronym>XML</acronym>, there are many popular books, including Erik Ray's <citetitle >Learning XML</citetitle><biblioref linkend="Ray03"/>.</para>
<remark>Norm: Do you have a preference for an XML reference?</remark>

<section xml:id="s.shorthistory">
<title>A Short DocBook History</title>

<para>DocBook is more than 15 years old. It began in 1991 as a joint
project of HaL Computer Systems and O'Reilly. Its popularity grew, and
eventually it spawned its own maintenance organization, the Davenport
Group. In mid-1998, it became a Technical Committee
(<acronym>TC</acronym>) of the Organization for the Advancement of
Structured Information Standards (<acronym>OASIS</acronym>).
</para>

<para>Starting with DocBook V5.0, DocBook is an XML vocabulary defined
with RELAX NG and Schematron. But DocBook is older than any of those
technologies. It was originally an <emphasis>SGML</emphasis> vocabulary
described with the standard <acronym>SGML</acronym> Document Type
Definition, or <acronym>DTD</acronym>.</para>

<section xml:id="s.history.haloreilly">
<title>The HaL and O'Reilly era</title>

<para><indexterm significance="normal">
  <primary>Open Software Foundation</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm significance="normal">
  <primary>troff markup (UNIX documentation)</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>UNIX</primary>
  <secondary>DocBook DTD, development</secondary>
</indexterm>The DocBook <acronym>DTD</acronym> was originally designed
and implemented by HaL Computer Systems and O'Reilly &amp; Associates
around 1991. It was developed primarily to facilitate the exchange of
<acronym>UNIX</acronym> documentation originally marked up in
<command>troff</command>. Its design appears to have been based partly
on input from <acronym>SGML</acronym> interchange projects conducted
by the Unix International and Open Software Foundation consortia.
</para>

<para><indexterm significance="normal">
  <primary>Davenport Group (DocBook maintenance)</primary>
</indexterm>When DocBook <acronym>V1.1</acronym> was published,
discussion about its revision and maintenance began in earnest in the
Davenport Group, a forum created by O'Reilly for computer
documentation producers. Version 1.2 was influenced strongly by Novell
and Digital.
</para>

<para>In 1994, the Davenport Group became an officially chartered
entity responsible for DocBook's maintenance. DocBook
<acronym>V1.2.2</acronym> was published simultaneously. The founding
sponsors of this incarnation of Davenport include the following
people:
<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem><simpara>Jon Bosak, Novell</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Dale Dougherty, O'Reilly &amp; Associates</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Ralph Ferris, Fujitsu <acronym>OSSI</acronym></simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Dave Hollander, Hewlett-Packard</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Eve Maler, Digital Equipment Corporation</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Murray Maloney, <acronym>SCO</acronym></simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Conleth O'Connell, HaL Computer Systems</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Nancy Paisner, Hitachi Computer Products</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Mike Rogers, SunSoft</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Jean Tappan, Unisys</simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="s.history.davenport">
<title>The Davenport era</title>

<para>Under the auspices of the Davenport Group, the DocBook
<acronym>DTD</acronym> began to widen its scope. It was now being used
by a much wider audience, and for new purposes, such as direct
authoring with <acronym>SGML</acronym>-aware tools, and publishing
directly to paper. As the largest users of DocBook, Novell and Sun had
a heavy influence on its design.
</para>

<para><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>DocBook DTD</primary>
  <secondary>releases, rules for new versions</secondary>
</indexterm>In order to help users manage change, the new Davenport
charter established the following rules for DocBook releases:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Minor versions (<quote>point releases</quote> such as
<acronym>V2.2</acronym>) could add to the markup model, but could not
change it in a backward-incompatible way. For example, a new kind of
list element could be added, but it would not be acceptable for the
existing itemized-list model to start requiring two list items inside
it instead of only one. Thus, any document conforming to version
<replaceable>n</replaceable>.0 would also conform to
<replaceable>n</replaceable>.<replaceable>m</replaceable>.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Major versions (such as <acronym>V3.0</acronym>) could
both add to the markup model and make backward-incompatible
changes. However, the changes would have to be announced in the last
major release.</para>
<para>In 2009, the Technical Committee updated this policy to allow
backward-incompatible changes in a major version, provided the change
is announced in a major or minor release at least six months in advance.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Major-version introductions must be separated by at
least a year.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>DocBook DTD</primary>
  <secondary>XML</secondary>
    <tertiary>XML-compliant version</tertiary>
</indexterm><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>XML</primary>
  <secondary>DocBook version compliant with</secondary>
</indexterm><acronym>V3.0</acronym> was released in January 1997.
After that time, although DocBook's audience continued to grow, many
of the Davenport Group stalwarts became involved in the
<acronym>XML</acronym> effort, and development slowed dramatically.
The idea of creating an official <acronym>XML</acronym>-compliant
version of DocBook was discussed, but not implemented at that time.
</para>

<para><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>OASIS</primary>
  <secondary>DocBook Technical Committee</secondary> </indexterm>In
  July, 1998, the sponsors moved the standards activities from the
  Davenport Group to <acronym>OASIS</acronym>, forming the
  <acronym>OASIS</acronym> DocBook Technical Committee with Eduardo
  Gutentag of Sun Microsystems as chair.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="s.history.oasis">
<title>The <acronym>OASIS</acronym> era</title>

<para>The
<link xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/">DocBook Technical
Commitee</link> is continuing the work started by the Davenport Group.
The transition from Davenport to <acronym>OASIS</acronym> was
very smooth, in part because the core design team remained
essentially the same. In MMM, YYYY, Norm Walsh became chair of
the Technical Committee.</para>

<para>DocBook <acronym>V3.1</acronym>, published in February 1999, was
the first <acronym>OASIS</acronym> release. It integrated a number of
changes that had been <quote>in the wings</quote> for some time.
</para>

<para>In February of 2001, OASIS made DocBook SGML V4.1 and DocBook
XML V4.1.2
<link xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/members/200102/msg00000.html">official
OASIS Specifications</link>.
</para>

<para>In October, 2005, the DocBook Technical Committee released the
first beta-test version of DocBook V5.0. Development of the DocBook
V4.x series continued in parallel with the development of V5.0. In
October, 2006, the DocBook Technical Committee released DocBook V4.5,
the last release in the V4.x series.</para>

<para>DocBook V5.0 became an official Committee Specification in June,
2009 and became an official OASIS standard in MMM, 2009. The committee
continues new DocBook development to ensure that the schema will
continue to meet the needs of its users.</para>
<para>In 2008, the Publisher's Sub-Committee was chartered to develop
and maintain official variants of DocBook in support of the publishing
industry. The subcommittee focuses on schema and
stylesheet customizations to support: periodicals as regularly
published technical notes or journals, book publishing (such as
business, legal, medical, and other non-technical domains),
educational textbooks and other document types as appropriate for this
industry.</para>
</section>
</section>
<section>
  <title>DocBook V5.0</title>
  <para>DocBook V5.0 represents a major step forward for DocBook. The
  differences between DocBook V4.x and V5.0 are quite radical in some
  aspects, but the basic idea behind DocBook is still the same, and
  almost all element names are unchanged. Because of this it is very
  easy to become familiar with DocBook V5.0 if you know any previous
  version of DocBook </para>


<section xml:id="introduction-ns">
<title>Finally in a namespace</title>

<para>All DocBook V5.0 elements are in the namespace
<uri>http://docbook.org/ns/docbook</uri>. <acronym>XML<alt>Extensible
Markup Language</alt></acronym> namespaces are used to distinguish
between different element sets. In the last few years, almost all new
XML grammars have used their own namespace. It is easy to
create compound documents that contain elements from different XML
vocabularies. DocBook V5.0 is following this design rule. Using
namespaces in your documents is very easy. Consider this
simple article marked up in DocBook V4.5:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<article>
  <title>Sample article</title>
  <para>This is a really short article.</para>
</article>]]></programlisting>

<para>The corresponding DocBook V5.0 article will look very similar:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" …>
  <title>Sample article</title>
  <para>This is a really short article.</para>
</article>]]></programlisting>

<para>The only change is the addition of a default namespace declaration
(<code>xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"</code>) on the root
element. This declaration applies the namespace to the root element and
all nested elements. Each
element is now uniquely identified by its local name and namespace.</para>

<note>
<para>The namespace name <uri>http://docbook.org/ns/docbook</uri> serves
only as an identifier. This resource is not fetched during processing
of DocBook documents, and you are not required to have an Internet
connection during processing. If you access the namespace URI with a browser,
you will find a short explanatory document about the namespace. In the
future this document will probably conform to (some version of) RDDL
and provide pointers to related resources.</para>
</note>

</section>

<section xml:id="introduction-rng">
<title>Relaxing with DocBook</title>

<para>For more than a decade, the DocBook schema was defined using a
DTD. However, DTDs have serious limitations, and DocBook V5.0 is thus
defined using a very powerful schema language called RELAX NG. Thanks
to RELAX NG, it is now much easier to create customized versions of
DocBook, and some content models are now cleaner and more
precise.</para>

<para>Using RELAX NG has an impact on the document prolog. The following
example shows the typical prolog of a DocBook V4.x document. The version of
the DocBook DTD (in this case 4.5) is indicated in the document type
declaration (!DOCTYPE) which points to a particular version of the
DTD.</para>

<example xml:id="ex.docbook45">
<title>DocBook V4.5 document</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
                         'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<article lang="en">
  <title>Sample article</title>
  <para>This is a very short article.</para>
</article>]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>In contrast, DocBook V5.0 does not depend on DTDs anymore. This
mean that there is no document type declaration and the version of DocBook
used is indicated with the <tag class="attribute">version</tag>
attribute instead.</para>

<example xml:id="ex.docbook5">
<title>DocBook V5.0 document</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Sample article</title>
  <para>This is a very short article.</para>
</article>]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>As you can see, DocBook V5.0 is built on top of existing XML
standards as much as possible, for example the <tag
class="attribute">lang</tag> attribute is superseded by the standard
<tag xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#sec-lang-tag"
class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> attribute.</para>

<para>Another fundamental change is that there is no direct indication
of the schema used. Later in this document, you will learn how you can
specify a schema to be used for document validation.</para>

<note>
<para>Although we recommend the RELAX NG schema for DocBook
V5.0, there are also DTD and W3C XML Schema versions available (see <xref
linkend="schemas"/>) for tools that do not yet support RELAX NG.</para>
</note>

</section>

<section xml:id="introduction-why-to-switch">
<title>Why switch to DocBook V5.0?</title>

<para>The simple answer is <quote>because DocBook V5.0 is the
future</quote>. Apart from this marketing blurb, there are also more
technical reasons:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis>DocBook V4.x is feature frozen.</emphasis>DocBook V4.5
is the last version of DocBook in the V4.x series. Any new DocBook
development, like the addition of new elements, will be done in
DocBook V5.0. It is only matter of time before useful, new elements
will be added into DocBook V5.0, but they are not likely to be back
ported into DocBook V4.x. DocBook V4.x will be in maintenance mode and
errata will be published if necessary. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis>DocBook V5.0 offers new functionality.</emphasis>
DocBook V5.0 provides significant improvements over DocBook V4.x. For
example there is general markup for annotations, a new and flexible
system for linking, and unified markup for information sections using
the <tag>info</tag> element.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis>DocBook V5.0 is more extensible.</emphasis> Having
DocBook V5.0 in a separate namespace allows you to easily mix DocBook
markup with other XML-based languages like SVG, MathML, XHTML or even
FooBarML.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis>DocBook V5.0 is easier to customize.</emphasis> RELAX
NG offers many powerful constructs that make customization much easier
than it would be using a DTD (see <xref linkend="customizations"/>).</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section xml:id="introduction-schemas">
<title>Schema jungle</title>

<para>Schemas for DocBook V5.0 are available in several formats at
<link xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/&version;/"/> (or the
mirror at <link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/xml/&version;/"/>).
Only the RELAX NG schema is normative
and it is preferred over the other schema languages.  However, for your
convenience there are also DTD and W3C XML Schema versions provided for DocBook
V5.0. But please note that neither the DTD nor the W3C XML schema are able to
capture all the constraints of DocBook V5.0. This mean that a
document that validates against the DTD or XML schema is not necessarily
valid against the RELAX NG schema and thus may not be a valid
DocBook V5.0 document.</para>

<para>DTD and W3C XML Schema versions of the DocBook V5.0 grammar are provided
as a convenience for users who want to use DocBook V5.0 with legacy tools
that don't support RELAX NG. Authors are encouraged to switch to RELAX
NG based tools as soon as possible, or at least to validate documents
against the RELAX NG schema before further processing.</para>

<para>Some document constraints can't be expressed in schema languages
like RELAX NG or W3C XML Schema. To check for these additional
constraints DocBook V5.0 uses Schematron.  We recommend that you
validate your document against both the RELAX NG and
Schematron schemas.</para>

<section xml:id="schemas">
<title>Where to get the schemas</title>

<para>The latest versions of schemas can be obtained from <link
xlink:href="http://docbook.org/schemas/5x.html"/>. At the time this was
written the latest version was &version;. Individual schemas are
available at the following locations:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>RELAX NG schema</term>
<listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/xml/&version;/rng/docbook.rng"/></para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>RELAX NG schema in compact syntax</term>
<listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/xml/&version;/rng/docbook.rnc"/></para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>DTD</term>
<listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/xml/&version;/dtd/docbook.dtd"/></para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>W3C XML Schema</term>
<listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/xml/&version;/xsd/docbook.xsd"/></para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Schematron schema with additional checks</term>
<listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/xml/&version;/sch/docbook.sch"/></para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>These schemas are also available from the mirror at
<link xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/&version;/"/>.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="docs">
<title>DocBook documentation</title>

<para>Detailed documentation about each DocBook V5.0 element is
presented in <link
xlink:href="http://docbook.org/tdg5/en/html/pt02.html">the reference part
of <citetitle>DocBook: The Definitive Guide</citetitle></link>.</para>

<note>
<para>Other parts of <citetitle>DocBook: The Definitive
Guide</citetitle> have not yet been updated to reflect the changes
made in DocBook V5.0. Please do not be confused by this.</para>
</note>
<indexterm startref="XMLgetstart" class="endofrange"/>
</section>

</section>

</section>
</chapter>
