<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:id="ch-gsxml">
<?dbhtml filename="ch01.html"?>
<title>Getting Started with <acronym>XML</acronym></title>
<info>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<para><indexterm xml:id="XMLgetstart" class="startofrange">
<primary>XML</primary><secondary>getting started</secondary>
</indexterm>This chapter used to provide a quick introduction
to structured markup. If you're not already familiar with
<acronym>XML</acronym>, consult one of the many popular books on
<acronym>XML</acronym>.</para>

<section xml:id="ch01-wheredocbook">
<title>How Does DocBook Fit In?</title>

<para><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>DocBook</primary>
  <secondary>history and overview</secondary>
</indexterm>DocBook is a very popular set of tags for describing
books, articles, and other prose documents, particularly technical
documentation. DocBook is an XML vocabulary normatively defined using
RELAX NG and Schematron.
</para>

<section xml:id="s.shorthistory">
<title>A Short DocBook History</title>

<para>DocBook is more than 15 years old. It began in 1991 as a joint
project of HaL Computer Systems and O'Reilly. Its popularity grew, and
eventually it spawned its own maintenance organization, the Davenport
Group. In mid-1998, it became a Technical Committee
(<acronym>TC</acronym>) of the Organization for the Advancement of
Structured Information Standards (<acronym>OASIS</acronym>).
</para>

<para>Starting with DocBook V5.0, DocBook is an XML vocabulary defined
with RELAX NG and Schematron. But DocBook is older than any of those
technologies. It was originally an <emphasis>SGML</emphasis> vocabulary
described with the standard <acronym>SGML</acronym> Document Type
Definition, or <acronym>DTD</acronym>.</para>

<section xml:id="s.history.haloreilly">
<title>The HaL and O'Reilly era</title>

<para><indexterm significance="normal">
  <primary>Open Software Foundation</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm significance="normal">
  <primary>troff markup (UNIX documentation)</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>UNIX</primary>
  <secondary>DocBook DTD, development</secondary>
</indexterm>The DocBook <acronym>DTD</acronym> was originally designed
and implemented by HaL Computer Systems and O'Reilly &amp; Associates
around 1991. It was developed primarily to facilitate the exchange of
<acronym>UNIX</acronym> documentation originally marked up in
<command>troff</command>. Its design appears to have been based partly
on input from <acronym>SGML</acronym> interchange projects conducted
by the Unix International and Open Software Foundation consortia.
</para>

<para><indexterm significance="normal">
  <primary>Davenport Group (DocBook maintenance)</primary>
</indexterm>When DocBook <acronym>V1.1</acronym> was published,
discussion about its revision and maintenance began in earnest in the
Davenport Group, a forum created by O'Reilly for computer
documentation producers. Version 1.2 was influenced strongly by Novell
and Digital.
</para>

<para>In 1994, the Davenport Group became an officially chartered
entity responsible for DocBook's maintenance. DocBook
<acronym>V1.2.2</acronym> was published simultaneously. The founding
sponsors of this incarnation of Davenport include the following
people:
<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem><simpara>Jon Bosak, Novell</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Dale Dougherty, O'Reilly &amp; Associates</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Ralph Ferris, Fujitsu <acronym>OSSI</acronym></simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Dave Hollander, Hewlett-Packard</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Eve Maler, Digital Equipment Corporation</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Murray Maloney, <acronym>SCO</acronym></simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Conleth O'Connell, HaL Computer Systems</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Nancy Paisner, Hitachi Computer Products</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Mike Rogers, SunSoft</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Jean Tappan, Unisys</simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="s.history.davenport">
<title>The Davenport era</title>

<para>Under the auspices of the Davenport Group, the DocBook
<acronym>DTD</acronym> began to widen its scope. It was now being used
by a much wider audience, and for new purposes, such as direct
authoring with <acronym>SGML</acronym>-aware tools, and publishing
directly to paper. As the largest users of DocBook, Novell and Sun had
a heavy influence on its design.
</para>

<para><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>DocBook DTD</primary>
  <secondary>releases, rules for new versions</secondary>
</indexterm>In order to help users manage change, the new Davenport
charter established the following rules for DocBook releases:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Minor versions (<quote>point releases</quote> such as
<acronym>V2.2</acronym>) could add to the markup model, but could not
change it in a backward-incompatible way. For example, a new kind of
list element could be added, but it would not be acceptable for the
existing itemized-list model to start requiring two list items inside
it instead of only one. Thus, any document conforming to version
<replaceable>n</replaceable>.0 would also conform to
<replaceable>n</replaceable>.<replaceable>m</replaceable>.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Major versions (such as <acronym>V3.0</acronym>) could
both add to the markup model and make backward-incompatible
changes. However, the changes would have to be announced in the last
major release.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Major-version introductions must be separated by at
least a year.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>DocBook DTD</primary>
  <secondary>XML</secondary>
    <tertiary>XML-compliant version</tertiary>
</indexterm><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>XML</primary>
  <secondary>DocBook version compliant with</secondary>
</indexterm><acronym>V3.0</acronym> was released in January 1997.
After that time, although DocBook's audience continued to grow, many
of the Davenport Group stalwarts became involved in the
<acronym>XML</acronym> effort, and development slowed dramatically.
The idea of creating an official <acronym>XML</acronym>-compliant
version of DocBook was discussed, but not implemented. (For more
detailed information about DocBook <acronym>V3.0</acronym> and plans
for subsequent versions, see <xref linkend="app-versions"/>.)
</para>

<para><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>OASIS</primary>
  <secondary>DocBook Technical Committee</secondary>
</indexterm>The sponsors wanted to close out Davenport in an orderly
way to ensure that DocBook users would be supported. It was suggested
that <acronym>OASIS</acronym> become DocBook's new home. An
<acronym>OASIS</acronym> DocBook Technical Committee was formed in
July, 1998, with Eduardo Gutentag of Sun Microsystems as chair.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="s.history.oasis">
<title>The <acronym>OASIS</acronym> era</title>

<para>The
<link xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/">DocBook Technical
Commitee</link> is continuing the work started by the Davenport Group.
The transition from Davenport to <acronym>OASIS</acronym> was
very smooth, in part because the core design team consists of
essentially the same individuals (we all just changed hats).
</para>

<para>DocBook <acronym>V3.1</acronym>, published in February 1999, was
the first <acronym>OASIS</acronym> release. It integrated a number of
changes that had been <quote>in the wings</quote> for some time.
</para>

<para>In February of 2001, OASIS made DocBook SGML V4.1 and DocBook
XML V4.1.2
<link xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/members/200102/msg00000.html">official
OASIS Specifications</link>.
</para>

<para>In October, 2005, the DocBook Technical Committee released the
first beta-test version of DocBook V5.0. Development of the DocBook
V4.x series continued in parallel with the development of V5.0. In
October, 2006, the DocBook Technical Committee released DocBook V4.5,
likely the last release in the V4.x series.</para>

<para>The official release of DocBook V5.0 is expected in August, 2007.</para>

<para>FIXME: say more about the motivations for V5.x.</para>

<para>The committee continues new DocBook development to ensure that
the schema will continue to meet the needs of its users.</para>

<indexterm startref="XMLgetstart" class="endofrange"/>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>