<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" xml:id="assemblies"
         revision="5.1">
<?db filename="ch06.html"?>
<info>
<title>DocBook Assemblies</title>
</info>

<para>One modern school of thought on technical documentation stresses
the development of independent units of documentation, often called
topics, rather than a single narrative. Instead of writing something
that DocBook users would easily recognize as a book consisting of a
preface, several consecutive chapters, and a few appendixes, the
author (or authors) write a set of discrete topics covering different aspects of
the system as if they were wholly independent.</para>

<para>In a typical online presentation system, for example the world
wide web or online help, each topic is a page that stands alone.
Except, of course, that just as no man is an island, no topic is
completely unrelated to the other topics that are available.</para>

<para>From any given topic, there may be topics of obviously related
interest. The nature of the relationships may vary. Some topics are
related by physical proximity (if you're interested in the ink
cartridges in a printer, you may also be interested in the print
head), others by their procedural nature (adding or replacing memory,
adding or replacing a hard drive, or even changing the CPU are all
topics that might logically follow a topic that describes how to open
the computer case).</para>

<para>In a single narrative, it is the responsibility of the author to
manage these relationships. He or she can reasonably assume that
anyone reading chapter 4 has read chapters 1, 2, and 3. If the reader
needs to be directed elsewhere, a cross reference can be used (for
example, “for more information on paper jams, see Section 3.5,
<citetitle>The Paper Path</citetitle>”).</para>

<para>In a topic-oriented system, authors are explicitly instructed to
write independent units. No linear order can be assumed and many forms
of explicit cross-reference are discouraged.</para>

<para>Documentation managers treat the library of available topics
very much as programmers treat libraries of available functions. Just
as any given program can pick and choose from the available libraries,
the documentation for any given system can pick and choose from the
available topics.</para>

<para>If you imagine a large documentation group managing the documentation
for several related systems (different models of printer, different
configurations of a software system, computers assembled from
different components, etc.) it's easy to see the appeal of topic-oriented
authoring.</para>

<para>In a successful deployment, you might find a library of say 1,000
topics which, taken together, document five or six related systems, each of
which uses 700-800 topics. Some topics are used in every system, many are
used in several systems, and a small number of topics are unique to a
specific system.</para>

<para>In order to make such a documentation platform functional, you
need not only the individual topics, but also some sort of “map” or
“assembly” file that describes which topics from the library are used,
what relationships exist between them and, at least for print
presentation, what linear order should be imposed upon them.</para>

<para>DocBook uses an <tag>assembly</tag> for this purpose.</para>

<section xml:id="physical">
<title>Physical structure</title>

<para>The notion of a DocBook <tag>assembly</tag> is predicated on a few
assumptions about the physical layout of the topics that are to be combined
together into units of documentation. We call the units of documentation
“structures” and the topics from which they are composed “resources”.</para>

<para>For the most part, we assume that resources exist as stand alone
documents accessible via URIs. The structures that result from assembling
the resources together may be a single file (as in a single PDF book) or
a collection of files (as in a web site or help system).</para>

<para>Other arrangements are possible, but for simplicity, we assume
that the resources are accessible via URIs and the resulting
structures can be written to the local filesystem as one or more
files.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="logical">
<title>Logical structure</title>

<para>Many features of an assembly allow the assembly process to
update metadata associated with a document, for example changing the
title or removing the metadata altogether. Throughout the description
of assemblies, we assume that all metadata always occurs inside an
<tag>info</tag> wrapper. In other words, although the following is
perfectly legal:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<chapter>
  <title>Chapter Title</title>
  <info>
    <pubdate>2009-11-23</pubdate>
  </info>
  <para>Some chapter content.</para>
</chapter>]]></programlisting>

<para>we always assume that this is instead represented with a single
<tag>info</tag> element:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<chapter>
  <info>
    <title>Chapter Title</title>
    <pubdate>2009-11-23</pubdate>
  </info>
  <para>Some chapter content.</para>
</chapter>]]></programlisting>

<para>Even in cases where there is no <tag>info</tag> element:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<section>
  <title>Section Title</title>
  <para>Some section content.</para>
</section>]]></programlisting>

<para>we assume one is present:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<section>
  <info>
    <title>Section Title</title>
  </info>
  <para>Some section content.</para>
</section>]]></programlisting>

<para>Authors <emphasis>are not</emphasis> required to author in this way
in order to use assemblies. Processing systems are to behave <emphasis>as
if</emphasis> they had.</para>

<para>The assumption that all metadata is always present in a single,
explicit <tag>info</tag> wrapper <emphasis>greatly</emphasis> simplifies
the exposition of assemblies without introducing any actual limitations.</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Assembly Files</title>

<para>An <tag>assembly</tag> has four major parts:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><tag>resources</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>Identifies a collection of topics. An assembly may have any number of
<tag>resources</tag> elements each identifying a collection of resources.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><tag>structure</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>Identifies a single artifact to be assembled. Such an artifact is a particular
collection of topics. An assembly may have any number of <tag>structure</tag> elements,
each identifying a single artifact.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><tag>relationships</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>Identifies relationships between resources. These relationships
may be manifested in any number of structures during assembly. An assembly
may have any number of <tag>relationships</tag> elements.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><tag>transforms</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>Identifies transformations that can be applied during assembly.
An assembly my have at most one <tag>transforms</tag> element, but it may contain
any number of <tag>transform</tag> elements.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<section xml:id="resources">
<title>Resources</title>

<para>Individual resources are identified through a <tag>resource</tag>
element:</para>

<programlisting language="xml">&lt;resource xml:id="topicA" href="uri/for/topicA.xml"/&gt;</programlisting>

<para>Here the resource “<literal>topicA</literal>” is associated with
the URI <uri>uri/for/topicA.xml</uri>. Relative URIs are made absolute
with respect to the element on which they appear. An optional <tag
class="attribute">description</tag> attribute may also be used to
provide a description of the resource.</para>

<note>
<title>Fragment Identifiers</title>
<para>The URI specified in the <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute
may include a fragment identifier, such as <uri>uri/for/topicA.xml#sectionid</uri>.
Which, if any, fragment identifier schemes are supported is implementation
defined.</para>
</note>

<para>A collection of resources may appear in a <tag>resources</tag>
wrapper. The primary motivation for the resources wrapper is to group
physically and logically colocated resources together. The
<tag>resources</tag> wrapper is a convenient place, for example, to specify
a common <tag class="attribute">xml:base</tag> or
<tag class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> and
<tag class="attribute">description</tag>.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="structures">
<title>Structures</title>

<para>Structures are where the real work is performed. There is considerable
tension between the goal of providing <tag>structure</tag> elements that are
simple for the simple cases and simultaneously allowing them to be complex
enough to describe the full richness of possibility.</para>

<para>This inherent tension is compounded by the fact that the nature of
<tag>structure</tag> outputs is naturally open ended. The goal is that
DocBook assemblies should be able to handle both the richness of the structures
that we produce today as well as the structures we will want to produce
tomorrow.</para>

<para>The principal task of the <tag>structure</tag> element is to
identify the resources that are to be combined for that structure.
The resulting structure may be delivered in any number of ways: as a single document,
help system, or web site, for example.</para>

<para>It is important to observe that the realized structure is often,
but not necessarily, a valid DocBook document. What is important is
not its validity from an authoring perspective, but rather its
validity with respect to what the downstream processor is
expecting.</para>

<para>For example, if the <tag>structure</tag> is defining a book, then the
realized structure should be a valid <tag>book</tag>. If, on the other hand,
what is defined is a help system, then the realized structure may be a
collection of nested <tag>topic</tag> elements. Even though authors
are not allowed to nest topics (per the DocBook 5.1 <tag>topic</tag>
element), the assembly process may be allowed to nest them.</para>

<para>A <tag>structure</tag> consists mostly of <tag>module</tag> elements.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="modules">
<title>Modules</title>

<para>The <tag>module</tag> element identifies a unit of structure.
The attributes and children of a module provide facilities for
selecting the content of the module and controlling its presentation.</para>

<para>A <tag>module</tag> with a <tag class="attribute">resourceref</tag>
attribute will pull in the content of that resource at that point in
the structure. If the module has a <tag class="attribute">renderas</tag> attribute,
then its attribute value replaces the name of the root element of the
resource during assembly. That allows you to convert a topic resource
to a chapter or section in the assembled DocBook.</para>

<para>A <tag>module</tag> without a <tag class="attribute">resourceref</tag>
attribute will create a new element in the assembled DocBook. It
should have a <tag class="attribute">renderas</tag> attribute to specify its
element name, and a <tag>merge</tag> child element to specify a title and any
other info data.</para>

<para>Module elements can nest to form hierarchies of content. A
nested module's content is added at the end of its parent module's
content, before the closing tag. Modules can be nested to any depth
needed. For example, if a set of resources are created as individual
topic elements, one module could render a topic as a chapter, and its
module children could render as sections within the chapter, with
further nested modules becoming subsections.</para>

<para>Keep in mind that nesting of content would normally be done in a
way that results in valid DocBook in the assembled document. However,
the output is not validated, so you can create invalid or custom
content with assemblies for any specific application.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="relationships">
<title>Relationships</title>

<para>A relationship, in the context of an assembly, is an assertion
that a particular collection of resources are related. The nature of
the relationship is specified with a <tag class="attribute">type</tag>
attribute. For example:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<relationship type="seealso">
  <instance linkend="tut1"/>
  <instance linkend="tut2"/>
  <instance linkend="task1"/>
</relationship>]]></programlisting>

<para>This asserts that there is a “seealso” relationship between these
resources. The processor might use this information to automatically generate
a “See Also” section at the end of any of these topics.</para>

<para>Relationships are often, but not necessarily, unordered. This
relationship establishes a path through a set of resources:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<relationship type="path">
  <info>
    <title>New User Introduction</title>
  </info>
  <instance linkend="over1"/>
  <instance linkend="over2"/>
  <instance linkend="task3"/>
  <instance linkend="cleanup"/>
</relationship>]]></programlisting>

<para>A sophisticated help system could use this path to guide a new
user through a sequence of resources.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="transformations">
<title>Transformations</title>

<para>An assembly can identify a collection of transformations that can
be used during the assembly process. This is intended primarily to enable
transforming sources that are not DocBook into DocBook so that they can
be merged into the assembly. Other uses are application dependent.</para>

<para>A transformation can be associated with a resource (for example,
to translate from some other format into DocBook), or with a module
(to address requirements beyond the limited transformation
capabilities of the assembly).</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<transforms>
  <transform grammar="dita" href="dita2db.xsl"/>
  <transform name="tutorial" href="db2tutorial.xsl"/>
  <transform name="art2pi" href="art2pi.xsl"/>
  <transform name="office" href="extractoffice.xsl"/>
</transforms>]]></programlisting>

<para>There are two ways to provide a transformation from a <tag>resource</tag>:
via the <tag class="attribute">grammar</tag> attribute or the <tag
class="attribute">transform</tag> attribute. If a <tag>resource</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">grammar</tag> attribute, the
<tag>transform</tag> with the matching
<tag class="attribute">grammar</tag> attribute will be selected. If it does
not have a <tag class="attribute">grammar</tag> attribute but it does have a
<tag class="attribute">transform</tag> attribute, the <tag>transform</tag> with
the specified name will be selected.</para>

<note>
<para>Not all systems may support arbitrary transformations, nor can
all systems support all possible transformation languages. To maximize
interoperability it is best to use as few explicit transformations
as possible, ideally none.</para>
</note>

<para>Given the transformations above, a DITA resource might be
included in the assembly:</para>

<programlisting language="xml">&lt;resource xml:id="overview" href="dita/over.xml"
          grammar="dita"/></programlisting>

<para>Whenever a module refers to this resource, it will receive the transformed,
DocBook result.</para>

<para>If a module needs to perform a transformation to get from one DocBook
format to another, it can name a transform as well:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<module resourceref="article">
  <output transform="tutorial"/>
</module>]]></programlisting>

<para>This will transform the module into a tutorial using the
<uri>db2tutorial.xsl</uri> transform specified in the matching
<tag>transform</tag> element.</para>

<para>If the <tag>output</tag> specifies a <tag
class="attribute">renderas</tag>, it is applied to the result of the
last transformation.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<info>
<title>Describing Structural Relationships With Assemblies</title>
<author>
  <personname>
    <firstname>Larry</firstname>
    <surname>Roland</surname>
  </personname>
</author>
</info>

<para>In addition to providing a mechanism for describing the
structure of the classical DocBook products such as books and
articles, the <tag class="element">assembly</tag> element can be used
to describe the relationships among non-linear collections of topics
such as are presented in Web sites and help systems. While help
systems can be produced by chunking a typical book into pieces; it is
important to emphasize the non-linear nature of the content during the
creation of it to avoid the presumption that a particular topic
follows its predecessor in the document.</para>

<para>Another characteristic of collections of topics such as help
systems and Web sites is that it can be, at times, important to
maintain explicit control over file names (to produce consistent
<acronym>URI</acronym>s or to reduce churn in source control systems).
The use of the assembly mechanism easily allows control over file
names for the delivered products.</para>

<para>It is also desirable, at times, to produce multiple output
formats for some of the non-linear documents, with different locations
for some portions of the content (the Index may go near the top of a
navigational hierarchy of the HTML delivery of a help system, while it
traditionally would be at the back of a printed version of a help
system). The ability to specify specific outputs for elements and
suppress them in other output formats supports this
requirement.</para>

<para>At this point, working through an example may be helpful.</para>

<section>
<title>Describing a Help System with an Assembly</title>

<para>This section describes the use of an assembly to describe the
hierarchical relationship among pages in a help system, and the use of
the <tag class="attribute">type</tag> attribute on assemblies to carry
information beyond the simple structure of a document. While there may
be other specific considerations applying the <tag class="element"
>assembly</tag> element to the description of a Web site, similar
considerations are likely to apply.</para>

<note>
<para>This is a simplified example, but based on a real system.</para>
</note>

<section>
<title>Background</title>

<para>This is the help system for a simple documentation build system
that has two Web-based screens that allow the user to build documents
(books rendered into PDF and chunked HTML and help systems that are
delivered with products using a Webhelp type system).</para>

<para>There are four tasks supported by the system. Two screens of
help are provided for the screens in the user interface, and the help
system organization has to comply with documentation standards.</para>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
  <title>Help System Structure</title>
  <para>Each entry in this list represents a node (HTML page) in the
  help system.</para>
  <listitem>
    <para>ToC</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Index</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Overview (Welcome)</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Tasks</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Building Documents</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Packaging Books for Publication</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Packaging Help for Submitting to Product Builds</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Packaging Documents (Books and Help) for
        Localization</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Screens and Menus</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Document Build Screen</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Document Packaging Screen</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Printable Version (PDF)</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Glossary</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Help on Help</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The Webhelp system delivers topics of help with a navigational
hierarchy on the left-hand side of the content presented for each
topic. The navigational hierarchy indicates the location of the topic
in the hierarchy by highlighting it and can be used to navigate to
other topics in the help system. Help is provided for each page in the
interface. In addition, a glossary is provided, with links from
glossterms in the body of the help system to the glossary along with
an index and full text search, that must be build across all the
topics in the help system.</para>

<para>In addition to being delivered using Webhelp, a printable
version of the help system is delivered with the help system in the
form of a PDF generated by walking the structure of the help system,
collecting the individual topics to create a book with the structure
derived from the hierarchical structure of the help system. However,
the PDF follows the conventions of printed books, putting the index at
the back of the book, and does not include the help on help
content.</para>

<para>In addition to the files for the Webhelp HTML and JavaScript,
supplementary files are delivered to allow merging with other help
systems and to support integration of the help on screens with the
product help buttons. Some of the HTML files are expected to have
standard names.</para>

<para>The following example assumes that the Webhelp transform has
been extended to support non-chunked generation of the system by
passing in a topic for each page to be rendered. The navigational
structure will be derived from the assembly.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>The Resources</title>

<para>A very simple set of resources is specified for the help system.
The file names are immaterial, and all the referenced file resources
are presumed to be topics except the glossary, which is simply a
glossary element (and usually derived from a glossary
database).</para>

<example>
<title>Resources for a Help System</title>
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <resources xml:base="some/path">
    <description>Resources for help system.</description>
    <resource xml:id="overview" href="overview.xml">
      <description>Overview of help system.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="task.build.doc" href="build.xml">
      <description>Describe how to build a document.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="pckg.intro" href="task-intro.xml">
      <description>Introduction to the packaging tasks.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="task.package.book.pub" href="package.xml">
      <description>Describe how to package a document for publication.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="task.package.help" href="help-package.xml">
      <description>Describe how to package a help system for submission to product
        build.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="task.package.l10n" href="l10n-package.xml">
      <description>Describe how to package source files for localization.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="screen.overview" href="screen-intro.xml">
      <description>Introductory text for screens and menus section.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="screen.build.doc" href="popup.xml">
      <description>Displayed when question mark icon on document build screen is
        clicked.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="screen.package" href="pkg-popup.xml">
      <description>Displayed when question mark icon on packaging screen is clicked.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="glossary" href="glossary.xml">
      <description>Glossary for help system.</description>
    </resource>
    <resource xml:id="help.on.help" href="help-on-help.xml">
      <description>How to use the help system.</description>
    </resource>
  </resources>]]></programlisting>
</example>
</section>

<section>
<title>Setting Up the Structure</title>

<para>The first few lines of the structure set up general things about
the help system:</para>

<example>
<title>Defining the Basics of the Help System</title>
<programlisting linenumbering="numbered" language="xml"><![CDATA[  <structure type="help.system">
    <info>
      <title>XIDI Build System Help</title>
      <titleabbrev>XIDI Help</titleabbrev>
    </info>
    <output outputformat="pdf" file="sys-book.pdf" renderas="book"/>
    <!-- The PDF output will be rendered into a file expected by the help
         system for the printable version of the help system. -->
    <output outputformat="webhelp" chunk="false" renderas="topic"/>
    <!-- The webhelp output will NOT be chunked and the default render
         (wherever a file name is specified) is as a topic.   IF the
         renderas on an output that is a child of structure is not treated as
         a default for specified files, a renderas has to be added to each of
         the webhelp output statements in the modules that specify a file. -->]]></programlisting>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">type</tag> attribute provides
information to the render system so that the auxiliary files for
merging and integration are built in addition to the Webhelp system.</para>
<para>The <tag class="element">output</tag> element for <tag
class="attvalue">pdf</tag> specifies the name of the file to use
and tells the render system to render a book as the printable
version of the help system.</para>
<para>The <tag class="element">output</tag> element for <tag
class="attvalue">webhelp</tag> suppresses chunking and sets the
default value for the webhelp output statements that do not have a
renderas attribute.</para>
</example>
</section>

<section>
<title>Standard Front End</title>
<para>By convention, the first two pages in the help system are the
table of contents and the index. However, in the book, the index goes
in the back.</para>

<example>
<title>The Front End</title>
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[    <module>
      <output outputformat="webhelp" file="sys-toc.html" renderas="toc"/>
    </module>
    <module>
      <output outputformat="webhelp" file="sys-index.html" renderas="index"/>
      <output outputformat="pdf" suppress="true"/>
    </module>]]></programlisting>
</example>
</section>

<section>
<title>Main Body of the Help System</title>

<para>The main content of the help system is broken into an overview
(Which can have lower-level topics below the main overview topic),
task descriptions, which may be grouped together or appear at the top
level if they are considered important enough to the user, and a set
of help pages for screens.</para>

<para>Each task description has a task element with a summary,
prerequisites, the procedure, and lists of related topics and tasks.
Help on screens always includes standard information such as how to
navigate to the screen and what tasks the screen is used to
accomplish. In complex systems, screens can be grouped together to
deal with things like Wizards and related screens and dialogs.</para>

<example>
<title>Middles Section of Help System</title>
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[    <module resourceref="overview">
      <output outputformat="webhelp" file="overview.html"/>
      <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="chapter"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task.build.doc">
      <output outputformat="webhelp" file="tsk-build-doc.html"/>
      <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="section"/>
    </module>
    <module>
      <output outputformat="webhelp" file="pckg-intro.html" renderas="preface"/>
      <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="chapter"/>
      <merge>
        <title>Packaging</title>
      </merge>
      <module resourceref="pckg.intro" contentonly="true" omittitles="true"/>

      <module resourceref="task.package.book.pub">
        <output outputformat="webhelp" file="tsk-pckg-book-pub.html"/>
        <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="section"/>
      </module>
      <module resourceref="task.package.help">
        <output outputformat="webhelp" file="tsk-pckg-help.html"/>
        <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="section"/>
      </module>
      <module resourceref="task.package.l10n">
        <output outputformat="webhelp" file="tsk-pckg-l10n.html"/>
        <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="section"/>
      </module>
    </module>
    <module>
      <output outputformat="webhelp" file="scr-overvw.html"/>
      <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="chapter"/>
      <merge>
        <title>Screens</title>
      </merge>
      <module resourceref="screen.overview" contentonly="true"
      omittitles="true"/>
      <module resourceref="screen.build.doc">
        <output outputformat="webhelp" file="scr-build.html"/>
        <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="section"/>
      </module>
      <module resourceref="screen.package">
        <output outputformat="webhelp" file="scr-package.html"/>
        <output outputformat="pdf" renderas="section"/>
      </module>
    </module>]]></programlisting>
</example>
</section>

<section>
<title>Standard Back End for the Help System</title>

<para>Once the main body of the help system is built, the standard
back end components are added.</para>

<example>
<title>Back End of Help System</title>
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[    <module>
      <output outputformat="webhelp"/> 
      <!-- No file, just want the link in the navigation. -->
      <output outputformat="pdf" suppress="true"/>
      <!-- Nothing in PDF. -->
      <merge>
        <title xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xl:href="sys-book.pdf">Printable Version (PDF)</title>
      </merge>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="glossary">
      <output outputformat="webhelp" file="sys-glossary.html"/>
      <!-- The help delivery system expects the glossary to be in a file named
           sys-glossary.html.-->
    </module>
    <module>
      <output outputformat="webhelp" suppress="true"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="help.on.help">
      <output outputformat="webhelp" file="help-on-help.html"/>
      <output outputformat="pdf" suppress="true"/>
      <!-- By convention help on how to use the help system is not included in
           the printable version of the help system and is stock, pulled from a
           library. -->
    </module>
  </structure>]]></programlisting>
</example>
</section>

<section>
<title>What Happens</title>

<para>Presuming an Ant (or other target based) build system for this
help system document, the following targets are meaningful for
building the document described by this structure.</para>

<variablelist>
  <title>Targets for Building the Help System</title>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>build.help</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Builds a help system with the following:</para>
      <simplelist columns="1" type="vert">
        <member>Webhelp files, including the full test search inverse
        index files</member>
        <member>XML files for merging with other help systems</member>
        <member>Properties files for integrating into product</member>
      </simplelist>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>build.pdf</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Build the PDF printable version</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>build.all</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Build the help system and the printable version, packaged
      into the same directory structure used to deliver the help
      system with the product, so that it can be zipped up for
      delivery into the product source control system.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</section>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="ex-book">
<title>Example: Assembling a Printed Book</title>

<para>For the purposes of this section, let's
assume that we have the following resources available:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<resources xml:base="tutorial/">
  <resource xml:id="tut1" href="tut1.xml"/>
  <resource xml:id="tut2" href="tut2.xml"/>
  <resource xml:id="tut3" href="tut3.xml"/>
  <resource xml:id="tut4" href="tut4.xml"/>
  <resource xml:id="tut5" href="tut5.xml"/>
</resources>

<resources xml:base="tasks/">
  <resource xml:id="task1" href="task1.xml"/>
  <resource xml:id="task2" href="task2.xml"/>
  <resource xml:id="task3" href="task3.xml"/>
  <resource xml:id="task4" href="task4.xml"/>
</resources>]]></programlisting>

<para>Further, let's assume that each of the tutorials and tasks is
authored as a standalone <tag>topic</tag>.</para>

<para>Our first challenge is to create a PDF user guide.
A subject matter expert has informed us that the proper linear
presentation for the user guide is tutorials 1 and 2, task 1, tutorial 3,
task 4, and an index.</para>

<para>Our first attempt at a structure might look like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<structure xml:id="user-guide">
  <output renderas="book"/>
  <module resourceref="tut1"/>
  <module resourceref="tut2"/>
  <module resourceref="task1"/>
  <module resourceref="tut3"/>
  <module resourceref="task4"/>
</structure>]]></programlisting>

<para>The <tag>output</tag> element identifies the kind of output to
be generated. There may be more than one type.
The <tag class="attribute">renderas</tag> attribute on the
<tag>output</tag> tells us that the realized structure should be a book.
</para>

<para>The <tag>module</tag> elements identify the resources to be included.
That's fine as far as it goes. Processing this <tag>structure</tag> will
create a realized structure that is a <tag>book</tag> (because that's what
the <tag class="attribute">renderas</tag> on the <tag>output</tag> tells
us) consisting of the tables of contents and the correct six topics:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <toc role="figures"/>
  <toc role="tables"/>
  <toc role="procedures"/>
  <topic xml:base="tutorial/tut1.xml">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    ...
  </topic>
  <topic xml:base="tutorial/tut2.xml">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    ...
  </topic>
  <topic xml:base="tasks/task1.xml">
    <title>Engaging the spindle</title>
    ...
  </topic>
  <topic xml:base="tutorial/tut3.xml">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    ...
  </topic>
  <topic xml:base="tasks/task4.xml">
    <title>Diagnosing spindle problems</title>
    ...
  </topic>
</book>]]></programlisting>

<para>The trouble is, that's not a valid <tag>book</tag>. Not only does it
consist of topics instead of the expected chapters and such, but it's lacking
necessary metadata like a title.</para>

<para>We can address the first problem by allowing
<tag>output</tag> elements inside modules.</para>

<para>Most high-level elements (<tag>chapter</tag>, <tag>appendix</tag>,
<tag>book</tag>, <tag>section</tag>, <tag>topic</tag>, etc.) in DocBook have
the same general structure: they contain an (optional) <tag>info</tag>
element followed by a collection of block elements.</para>

<para>The semantic of <tag class="attribute">renderas</tag> in a
<tag>module</tag> that points to a resource is that it renames the
root element of that resource. This simple transformation will allow us
to turn all those topics into elements more appropriate for <tag>book</tag>
content. (We'll consider how to address the situation where more complex
transformation is necessary later.)</para>

<para>We can address the problem of missing metadata by creating a new
<tag>resource</tag> that contains an <tag>info</tag> element containing
the appropriate metadata and then pointing to it. Alternatively, you
can supply a <tag>merge</tag> element containing metadata for the
structure. The <tag>merge</tag> element has the same content
model as <tag>info</tag>. Metadata elements that you include in the
<tag>merge</tag> element are applied to the output element for the
<tag>structure</tag>.</para>

<para>With these amendments, here's our new structure:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<structure xml:id="user-guide">
  <output renderas="book"/>
  <merge>
    <title>Widget User Guide</title>
  </merge>
  <module resourceref="full-toc"/>
  <module resourceref="tut1">
    <output renderas="chapter"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="tut2"/>
  <module resourceref="task1"/>
  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="task4">
    <output renderas="section"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="index"/>
</structure>]]></programlisting>

<para>The realized structure that this produces is:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Widget User Guide</title>
  </info>
  <toc/>
  <toc role="figures"/>
  <toc role="tables"/>
  <toc role="procedures"/>
  <chapter xml:base="tutorial/tut1.xml">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    ...
  </chapter>
  <chapter xml:base="tutorial/tut2.xml">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    ...
  </chapter>
  <chapter xml:base="tasks/task1.xml">
    <title>Engaging the spindle</title>
    ...
  </chapter>
  <appendix xml:base="tutorial/tut3.xml">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    ...
  </appendix>
  <appendix xml:base="tasks/task4.xml">
    <title>Diagnosing spindle problems</title>
    ...
  </appendix>
  <index/>
</book>]]></programlisting>

<para>That realized structure is a valid <tag>book</tag> so you would
expect the processing system to produce the correct results.</para>

<para>Except that it's not the right book. Upon further review by our subject
matter expert, it's been decided that tutorial 3 and task 4 shouldn't
be separate appendixes, they should instead both be sections in a single
appendix called “Troubleshooting”.</para>

<para>We can address this issue with nested modules. Instead of having
separate top-level modules for the tutorial and task, we'll make them
subordinate modules in a new top-level module:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<structure xml:id="user-guide">
  <output renderas="book"/>
  <merge>
    <title>Widget User Guide</title>
  </merge>
  <module resourceref="full-toc"/>
  <module resourceref="tut1">
    <output renderas="chapter"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="tut2">
    <output renderas="chapter"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="task1">
    <output renderas="chapter"/>
  </module>
  <module>
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <merge>
      <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    </merge>
    <module resourceref="tut3">
      <output renderas="section"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task4">
      <output renderas="chapter"/>
    </module>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="index"/>
</structure>]]></programlisting>

<para>The semantics of <tag class="attribute">renderas</tag> on a module
that does not have a <tag class="attribute">resourceref</tag> is that it
simply generates that element.</para>

<para>The realized document is now:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Widget User Guide</title>
  </info>
  <toc/>
  <toc role="figures"/>
  <toc role="tables"/>
  <toc role="procedures"/>
  <chapter xml:base="tutorial/tut1.xml">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    ...
  </chapter>
  <chapter xml:base="tutorial/tut2.xml">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    ...
  </chapter>
  <chapter xml:base="tasks/task1.xml">
    <title>Engaging the spindle</title>
    ...
  </chapter>
  <appendix>
    <info>
      <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    </info>
    <section xml:base="tutorial/tut3.xml">
      <title>Troubleshooting</title>
      ...
    </section>
    <section xml:base="tasks/task4.xml">
      <title>Diagnosing spindle problems</title>
      ...
    </section>
  </appendix>
  <index/>
</book>]]></programlisting>

<para>That's probably not quite what was intended. Given that tutorial 3
has the title “Troubleshooting”, what we probably wanted was to make that
tutorial the <tag>appendix</tag> and make the task a subordinate section
of that appendix.</para>

<para>We can achieve that by nesting the modules differently:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <module resourceref="task4">
      <output renderas="section"/>
    </module>
  </module>]]></programlisting>

<para>Now the <tag>appendix</tag> in the realized structure has the form
that we want:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <appendix xml:base="tutorial/tut3.xml">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    ...
    <section xml:base="tasks/task4.xml">
      <title>Diagnosing spindle problems</title>
      ...
    </section>
  </appendix>]]></programlisting>

<para>If a module “A” is nested within a module “B” that refers to a
resource, the result of processing “A” is inserted into “B” as the last
child of “B”. (In the case of several nested modules, they are inserted
as the last children in the order specified.)</para>

<para>After further review of the content, the subject matter expert decides
that tutorial 5 and task 3 are also relevant to trouble shooting. Tutorial
5 also has the title “Troubleshooting” and naturally follows tutorial 3.
Task 3 is about diagnosing bearing issues.</para>

<para>It's easy to combine them the new content into the appendix:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <module resourceref="tut5">
      <output renderas="section"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task4"/>
    <module resourceref="task3"/>
  </module>]]></programlisting>

<para>but that doesn't produce a pleasing result:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <appendix xml:base="tutorial/tut3.xml">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    ...
    <section xml:base="tutorial/tut5.xml">
      <title>Troubleshooting</title>
      ...
    </section>
    <section xml:base="tasks/task4.xml">
      <title>Diagnosing spindle problems</title>
      ...
    </section>
    <section xml:base="tasks/task3.xml">
      <title>Diagnosing bearing problems</title>
      ...
    </section>
  </appendix>]]></programlisting>

<para>What we really want to do is combine tutorials 3 and 5, not make 5
a subordinate section of 3. While we're at it, let's change the title of
the appendix to “Troubleshooting spindle and bearing problems” since that's
what it's really about.</para>

<para>We can solve the first problem with the
<tag class="attribute">contentonly</tag> attribute on <tag>module</tag>:
</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <module resourceref="tut5" contentonly="true"/>
    <module resourceref="task4">
      <output renderas="section"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task3"/>
  </module>]]></programlisting>

<para>If
<tag class="attribute">contentonly</tag> is <literal>true</literal>,
then only the content of the document element, and not the document element
itself, is included.</para>

<para>The realized structure for this appendix is now:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <appendix xml:base="tutorial/tut3.xml">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    ...
    ...content (only) of tutorial 5...
    <section xml:base="tasks/task4.xml">
      <title>Diagnosing spindle problems</title>
      ...
    </section>
    <section xml:base="tasks/task3.xml">
      <title>Diagnosing bearing problems</title>
      ...
    </section>
  </appendix>]]></programlisting>

<para>There are two ways that we can change the title. The first uses only
semantics we've already encountered:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <module>
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <merge>
      <title>Troubleshooting spindle and bearing problems</title>
    </merge>
    <module resourceref="tut3" contentonly="true"/>
    <module resourceref="tut5" contentonly="true"/>
    <module resourceref="task4">
      <output renderas="section"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task3"/>
  </module>]]></programlisting>

<para>Instead, we introduce one more convention: if a <tag>module</tag>
refers to another resource <emphasis>and</emphasis> contains a
<tag>merge</tag> element, then the elements within that
<tag>merge</tag> replace any elements of the same name in the
referenced resource's metadata. (If the referenced resource has no
metadata, then the specified <tag>merge</tag> becomes an
<tag>info</tag> and is inserted as the first child of the referenced
resource.)</para>

<para>The second approach uses this convention:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <merge>
      <title>Troubleshooting spindle and bearing problems</title>
    </merge>
    <module resourceref="tut5" contentonly="true"/>
    <module resourceref="task4">
      <output renderas="section"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task3"/>
  </module>]]></programlisting>

<para>In the realized structure for this example, the appendix
metadata includes everything in tutorial 3's metadata, with the title
changed as indicated.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="ex-html">
<title>Example: Assembling an Online Book</title>

<para>This example extends the book example, see <xref
linkend="ex-book"/>. In addition to the printed user guide, we want to
produce an online user guide. The online guide is, by design, a
straightforward, linear rendering of the book. We'll look at a more
intricately structured example later.</para>

<para>We could create a separate assembly for the online guide, but it
will be better in the long run if we can manage the structure of the user
guide in one place.</para>

<para>The first step is to create a new output type:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<structure xml:id="user-guide">
  <output outputformat="book" renderas="book"/>
  <output outputformat="web" renderas="book"/>
  <merge>
    <title>Widget User Guide</title>
  </merge>
  <module resourceref="full-toc"/>
  <module resourceref="tut1">
    <output renderas="chapter"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="tut2"/>
  <module resourceref="task1"/>
  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <merge>
      <title>Troubleshooting spindle and bearing problems</title>
    </merge>
    <module resourceref="tut5" contentonly="true"/>
    <module resourceref="task4">
      <output renderas="section"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task3"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="index"/>
</structure>]]></programlisting>

<para>Now we can process this structure either as a “book” type structure
or a “web” type structure. At the moment, there's no difference between them.
Let's consider some of the changes we need to make for the
online site:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>We want to control the names of the HTML documents produced.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>We want to control how chunking is performed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>We want to suppress some “print only” content.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The first two of these we can address with <tag>output</tag>
elements:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<structure xml:id="user-guide">
  <output outputformat="book" renderas="book"/>
  <output outputformat="web" renderas="book" file="user-guide.html"/>
  <merge>
    <title>Widget User Guide</title>
  </merge>
  <module resourceref="full-toc">
    <output outputformat="web" chunk="false"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="tut1">
    <output renderas="chapter"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="tut2"/>
  <module resourceref="task1"/>
  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <merge>
      <title>Troubleshooting spindle and bearing problems</title>
    </merge>
    <module resourceref="tut5" contentonly="true"/>
    <module resourceref="task4">
      <output renderas="section"/>
      <output outputformat="web" chunk="false"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task3"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="index">
    <output outputformat="web" file="book-index.html"/>
  </module>
</structure>]]></programlisting>

<para>Specifying a <tag class="attribute">file</tag> on an <tag>output</tag>
tells the assembly where to write the chunk. (If it occurs on a module which
is not chunked, it is simply ignored.) The <tag class="attribute">chunk</tag>
attribute can be used to specify which modules should (or should not) be
placed in separate chunks. The implied value on modules where it is not
specified depends on the name of the rendered element and the output format.</para>

<para>When processing a module, all of the relevant output directives are
combined. An <tag>output</tag> is relevant if it does not specify an
output format or if the format specified matches the processing that is being
performed. If conflicting values are specified for any attribute, the last
value specified (in document order) is used.</para>

<para>To exclude (or include) content, we add the
<tag>filterout</tag> (and <tag>filterin</tag>) elements to the assembly.
Each may have a <tag class="attribute">outputformat</tag> and specifies some number
of effectivity values. (The processor will have to be configured to profile before
assembling, of course.)</para>

<para>If no conditions are specified on <tag>filterout</tag>, the
module is unconditionally excluded. (Specifying no conditions on a
<tag>filterin</tag> has no effect.)</para>

<para>If filters are used at the <tag>structure</tag> level, they apply to
the entire document. If they are used at the <tag>module</tag> level, they
apply only to that module.</para>

<para>With filters, our <tag>structure</tag> might look like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<structure xml:id="user-guide">
  <output outputformat="book" renderas="book"/>
  <output outputformat="web" renderas="book" file="user-guide.html"/>
  <filterout outputformat="web" condition="print"/>
  <merge>
    <title>Widget User Guide</title>
  </merge>
  <module resourceref="full-toc">
    <output outputformat="web" chunk="false"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="tut1">
    <output renderas="chapter"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="tut2">
    <filterin outputformat="web" condition="print"/>
    <filterout outputformat="web" userlevel="advanced"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="task1"/>
  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <output renderas="appendix"/>
    <merge>
      <title>Troubleshooting spindle and bearing problems</title>
    </merge>
    <module resourceref="tut5" contentonly="true"/>
    <module resourceref="task4">
      <output renderas="section"/>
      <output outputformat="web" chunk="false"/>
    </module>
    <module resourceref="task3"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="index">
    <filterout outputformat="web"/>
  </module>
</structure>]]></programlisting>

<para>This <tag>structure</tag> applies the following filters when rendering
for the web: print only content is excluded globally; in tutorial 2,
print only content <emphasis>is</emphasis> included, but advanced material
is excluded; and the entire index is excluded.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="ex-ref">
<title>Example: Assembling an Online Reference</title>

<para>The online reference differs from the preceding book-based examples
in that no total, linear order is imposed on the content. Instead, navigation
is performed either by search (which is outside the scope of assemblies)
or through related links.</para>

<para>Using the resources defined in <xref linkend="ex-book"/>, here's
a plausible <tag>structure</tag> for our online reference.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<structure xml:id="user-guide">
  <output renderas="topic"/>
  <filterout outputformat="web" condition="print"/>
  <merge>
    <title>Widget Reference</title>
  </merge>
  <module resourceref="tut1"/>
  <module resourceref="tut2"/>
  <module resourceref="task1"/>
  <module resourceref="tut3">
    <merge>
      <title>Troubleshooting spindle and bearing problems</title>
    </merge>
    <module resourceref="tut5" contentonly="true"/>
    <module resourceref="task4"/>
    <module resourceref="task3"/>
  </module>
  <module resourceref="tut4"/>
  <module resourceref="task2"/>
  <module resourceref="index"/>
</structure>]]></programlisting>

<para>The resulting realized structure will be a nested set of
<tag>topic</tag> elements. Topics don't nest in DocBook (at least
in DocBook 5.1), so this isn't a valid DocBook document.
However, the nested topics provide a navigational structure for the
online presentation. The rendering system is, we assume, smart enough
to render each of the topics separately, as if they were all top-level
siblings.</para>

</section>
</chapter>
