<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<info>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><?tdg-refentrytitle?></refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo role="element">indexterm</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo role="pattern">db.indexterm.singular</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname><?tdg-refname?></refname>
  <refpurpose><?tdg-refpurpose?></refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<?tdg-refsynopsisdiv?>

<refsection condition="ref.description">
<title>Description</title>


<para>An <tag>indexterm</tag> identifies text that is to be placed in the
index. In the simplest case, the placement of the <tag>indexterm</tag>
in the document identifies the location of the term in the text. In
other words, the <tag>indexterm</tag> is placed in the flow of the
document at the point where the <tag>indexentry</tag> in the
<tag>index</tag> should point. In other cases, attributes on
<tag>indexterm</tag> are used to identify the location of the term in
the text.
</para>

<para>An <tag>indexterm</tag> marks either a single point in the
document or a range. A single point is marked with an
<tag>indexterm</tag> placed in the text at the point of reference.
There are two ways to identify a range of text:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Place an <tag>indexterm</tag> at the beginning of the range with
<tag class="attribute">class</tag> set to
<tag class="attvalue">startofrange</tag> and
give this term an <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag>.
Place another <tag>indexterm</tag> at the end of the range with
<tag class="attribute">startref</tag> pointing to the 
<tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> of the starting <tag>indexterm</tag>.
This second <tag>indexterm</tag> must be empty.
</para>

<para>The advantage of this method is that the range can span unbalanced element
boundaries.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Place the <tag>indexterm</tag> anywhere you like and point to the
element that contains the range of text you wish to index with the
<tag class="attribute">zone</tag> attribute on the <tag>indexterm</tag>.
Note that <tag class="attribute">zone</tag> is defined as 
<literal>IDREFS</literal> so a single <tag>indexterm</tag> can point to
multiple ranges.
</para>

<para>The advantage of this method is that <tag>indexterm</tag>s can be 
collected together or even stored totally outside the flow of the
document (in the <tag>info</tag> for example).
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<refsection><title>Processing expectations</title>
<para><tag>indexterm</tag>s are suppressed in the primary text flow,
although they contribute to the population of an index and serve as
anchors for cross references. Under no circumstances is the actual
content of <tag>indexterm</tag> rendered in the primary flow.
</para>

<para>Authors can choose to have several types of indexes, for example,
function, command, and concept indexes. This can be achieved in DocBook
with the <tag class="attribute">type</tag> attribute. All of the
<tag>indexterm</tag>s with a particular <tag class="attribute">type</tag>
will be collected together in the <tag>index</tag> with the same
<tag class="attribute">type</tag>.</para>
</refsection>

<?tdg-attributes?>
<?tdg-parents?>
<?tdg-children?>

</refsection>

<?tdg-seealso?>

<refsection condition="ref.examples">
<title>Examples</title>

<programlisting><xi:include href="example.1.xml" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>An example of a zone.</para>

<programlisting><xi:include href="example.3.xml" parse="text"/></programlisting>

</refsection>

</refentry>