<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<info>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><?tdg-refentrytitle?></refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo role="element">indexterm</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo role="pattern">db.indexterm.endofrange</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname><?tdg-refname?></refname>
  <refpurpose><?tdg-refpurpose?></refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<?tdg-refsynopsisdiv?>

<refsection condition="ref.description">
<title>Description</title>

<para>An <tag>indexterm</tag> identifies text that is to be placed in
the index. In the simplest case, the placement of the
<tag>indexterm</tag> in the document identifies the location of the
term in the text. In other words, the <tag>indexterm</tag> is placed
in the flow of the document at the point where the
<tag>indexentry</tag> in the <tag>index</tag> should point. In other
cases, attributes on <tag>indexterm</tag> are used to identify the
location of the term in the text.
</para>

<para>The <tag>indexterm</tag>s mark either a single point in the document
or a range.  A single point is marked with an <tag>indexterm</tag>
placed in the text at the point of reference.
There are two ways to identify a range of text:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Place an <tag>indexterm</tag> at the beginning of the range with
<tag class="attribute">class</tag> set to <literal>StartOfRange</literal> and
give this term an <tag class="attribute">id</tag>.
Place another <tag>indexterm</tag> at the end of the range with
<tag class="attribute">startref</tag> pointing to the 
<tag class="attribute">id</tag> of the starting <tag>indexterm</tag>.
This second <tag>indexterm</tag> must be empty.
</para>
<para>The advantage of this method is that the range can span unbalanced element
boundaries.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Place the <tag>indexterm</tag> anywhere you like and point to the
element that contains the range of text you wish to index with the
<tag class="attribute">zone</tag> attribute on the <tag>indexterm</tag>.
Note that <tag class="attribute">zone</tag> is defined as 
<literal>IDREFS</literal> so a single <tag>indexterm</tag> can point to
multiple ranges.
</para>
<para>The advantage of this method is that <tag>indexterm</tag>s can be 
collected together or even stored totally outside the flow of the
document (in the meta for example).
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<refsection><title>Processing expectations</title>
<para>The <tag>indexterm</tag>s are suppressed in the primary text flow, although they
contribute to the population of an index and serve as anchors for
cross references.
Under no
circumstances is the actual content of <tag>indexterm</tag>
rendered in the primary flow.
</para>

<para>It is possible to construct index terms that are difficult to parse at
best and totally illogical at worst.  Consider the following:

<screen>

&lt;indexterm class='startofrange' zone="id1 id2"&gt;...&lt;/indexterm&gt;

</screen>
</para>

<para>There is no way that this can fit into the semantics of an
<tag>indexterm</tag>.  Although it claims to be the start of a range,
it does not have an 
<tag class="attribute">id</tag> for the end-of-range
<tag>indexterm</tag> to point back to.
In addition, it includes zoned terms, and mixing the two
different methods for indicating a range in the same <tag>indexterm</tag>
is probably a bad idea.
</para>
</refsection>


<?tdg-attributes?>
<?tdg-parents?>
<?tdg-children?>

</refsection>

<?tdg-seealso?>

</refentry>