<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
          xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
          xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
<info>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><?tdg-refentrytitle?></refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo role='element'>inlinemediaobject</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo role='pattern'>db.inlinemediaobject</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname><?tdg-refname?></refname>
  <refpurpose><?tdg-refpurpose?></refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<?tdg-refsynopsisdiv?>

<refsection condition='ref.description'>
<title>Description</title>

<para>The <tag>inlinemediaobject</tag> element contains a set of alternative
“graphical objects”: <tag>videoobject</tag>,
<tag>audioobject</tag>, and <tag>imageobject</tag>. Additional
textual descriptions may be provided with <tag>textobject</tag>s.
</para>

<para>An <tag>inlinemediaobject</tag> provides a wrapper for a set of alternative
presentations for some, usually graphical, information. It is the “inline”
equivalent of <tag>mediaobject</tag>.</para>

<para>In almost all contexts where text is allowed,
<tag>inlinemediaobject</tag> is also allowed. This allows an author to
provide a graphic for a character or glyph, for example, one that is
not available in the publisher's fonts or perhaps is not available in
Unicode. Authors should exercise care when using <tag>inlinemediaobject</tag>
for this purpose as graphics may be difficult or impossible to display
in some contexts on some presentation systems.</para>

<refsection xml:id="dbreproc.inlinemediaobject">
<title>Processing expectations</title>

<para><?tdg gentext='format.inline'?>
</para>

<para>If possible, the processing system should use the content of the
first object within the <tag>inlinemediaobject</tag>.  If the first
object cannot be used, the remaining objects should be
considered in the order that they occur.  A processor should use
the first object that it can, although it is free to choose any
of the remaining objects if the primary one cannot be used.
</para>

<para>Under no circumstances may more than one object in an
<tag>inlinemediaobject</tag> be used or presented at the same time.
</para>

<para>For example, an <tag>inlinemediaobject</tag> might contain a high
resolution image, a low resolution image, and
a text description. For print publishing, the high resolution image is used;
for online systems, either the high or low resolution image is used,
possibly including the text description as an online alternative.
In a text-only environment, the text description is used.
</para>
</refsection>

<?tdg-attributes?>
<?tdg-parents?>
<?tdg-children?>

</refsection>

<?tdg-seealso?>

<refsection condition='ref.examples'>
<title>Examples</title>

<programlisting><xi:include href='example.1.xml' parse='text'/></programlisting>

<anchor xml:id='ex.os.inlinemediaobject.1' role='HACK-ex.out.start'/>
<xi:include href='example.1.xml' xpointer='/1/2'/>
<anchor xml:id='ex.oe.inlinemediaobject.1' role='HACK-ex.out.end'/>

</refsection>

</refentry>
