<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/docbook-ng'
          xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
          xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
<info>
  <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
</info>

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><?tdg-refentrytitle?></refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo role='element'>inlinemediaobject</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo role='pattern'>db.inlinemediaobject</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname><?tdg-refname?></refname>
  <refpurpose><?tdg-refpurpose?></refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<?tdg-refsynopsisdiv?>

<refsection condition='ref.description'>
<title>Description</title>


<para><tag>InlineMediaObject</tag> contains a set of alternative
“graphical objects.” In DocBook V3.1, three types of
external graphical objects are defined: <tag>VideoObject</tag>s,
<tag>AudioObject</tag>s, and <tag>ImageObject</tag>s. Additional
textual descriptions may be provided with <tag>TextObject</tag>s.
</para>

<refsection xml:id="dbreproc.inlinemediaobject"><title>Processing expectations</title>
<para><?tdg gentext='format.inline'?>
</para>
<para>The primary purpose of the <tag>InlineMediaObject</tag> is to provide
a wrapper around a set of alternative presentations of the same
information.
</para>
<para>If possible, the processing system should use the content of the
first object within the <tag>InlineMediaObject</tag>.  If the first
object cannot be used, the remaining objects should be
considered in the order that they occur.  A processor should use
the first object that it can, although it is free to choose any
of the remaining objects if the primary one cannot be used.
</para>
<para>Under no circumstances should more than one object in an
<tag>InlineMediaObject</tag> be used or presented at the same time.
</para>
<para>For example, an <tag>InlineMediaObject</tag> might contain a high
resolution image, a low resolution image, and
a text description. For print publishing, the high resolution image is used;
for online systems, either the high or low resolution image is used,
possibly including the text description as an online alternative.
In a text-only environment, the text description is used.
</para>
</refsection>

<?tdg-parents?>
<?tdg-children?>

</refsection>

<?tdg-seealso?>

<!-- FIXME: add examples -->

</refentry>
